music
music
applause
applause
Our feast of knowledge tonight
我們今天晚上的知識饗宴
Our monthly feast of knowledge
我們一個月一次的知識饗宴
I am very happy to invite the director of our physics institute today
今天很高興請到我們物理所的所長
Director Li Dingguo
李定國所長
He is also a Special Review Researcher of the Institute
他也是本院的特評研究員
Director Li was born in 1976
李所長是1976年
Ph.D. from Brown University
就拿到美國布朗大學的博士
He was also at Virginia Tech
他也曾經在Virginia Tech
after a while
交過一段時間
and then back to Taiwan
然後再回臺灣
He has been back to Taiwan for a long time
他也回臺灣很久了
I believe everyone in academia knows him
我相信學術界裡面大家都知道他
Also served in the hospital
在院裡面也擔任過
Executive Secretary of our Academic Association
我們學術總會的執行祕書
This is an academic program within the Chancellery
這個是總理所有院內的學術計畫
And review and so on
還有審查等等的工作
at the National Science Council
那在國科會
which is now the Ministry of Science and Technology
也就是現在的科技部
He also served as the director of the Theory Center
也曾經擔任過理論中心的主任
Program host at the Nano Center, etc.
奈米中心的計畫主持人等等
That
那
Dr. Li has also won the membership of the Physical Society of the Republic of China
李博士也獲得過中華民國物理學會的會事
Also a meeting of the British Physical Society
也是英國物理學會的會事
Also a meeting of the American Physical Society
也是美國物理學會的會事
Needless to say, he has won numerous awards
得獎無數當然不用說
We have the Outstanding Honor Award of Houjindui in China
我們國內有猴金堆傑出榮譽獎
National Science Council Outstanding Research Award
國科會傑出研究獎
And the Outstanding Talent Award from the Outstanding Talent Foundation, etc.
還有傑出人才基金會的傑出人才獎做等等
Then I always say that our basic science
那我每次都說我們這個基礎科學
To say that everyone knows
要來講到大家都了解
is working very hard
是在很辛苦
But every time we look for a speaker
不過我們每次找的演講人都
satisfies power
滿足了權力
I believe
我相信
Although everyone read the topic today, it seems a bit
雖然今天大家看了題目好像有點
Seeking to generate higher overheating
追尋產生更高超温
Mechanism of superconducting temperature
超導溫度的機制
high temperature superconductivity
高溫超導
I believe everyone has heard of this term
我相信這個名詞大家有聽過
he is trying to put
他是試圖要把
whole process mechanism
整個的過程機制
to tell everyone
要說給大家聽
I think
我想
We use these two hours
這個我們利用這兩個小時
I believe
我相信
Director must
理所長一定
Let everyone know how this high-temperature superconductivity came about
會讓大家對這個高溫超導是怎麼來的
the future potential
那將來的potential
future
將來的
this
這個
practical application
實際的應用
people say you can see
大家就說你可以看到
He has already placed a resignation in front of this
他前面已經擺了一個辭服的這個
Our goal is to say
我們目標就是說
this resignation train
這個辭服列車
Actually now
其實現在
Already have how to take a step further
現在已經有 如何更提高一步
I believe we will gain a lot tonight
我相信我們今天晚上一定收穫很多
We welcome Director Li
我們歡迎李所長
Thank you Vice President Wang
謝謝王副院長
Thank you all for coming to the party tonight
謝謝大家晚上來參加這個聚會
This is just now Vice President Wang also said that this is a big challenge
這個是剛才王副院長也說了這是一個很大的挑戰
because it's me
因為這是我
first
第一次
to use
要用
Talk about the superconducting mechanism in a popular speech
通俗演講的方式講這個超導的機制
This is something that everyone may have heard of but may not know about superconductivity.
這個是大家可能都聽過但是可能都不了解超導
The reason why I took this name was because of the magic I thought about this research topic is
的神奇讓我取這個名字的原因我想了半天因為我對這個研究題目是
most interested have done
最有興趣已經做了
decades of this
幾十年的這個
Superconducting
超導的
The problem is this is what I've been looking for
問題那這個是我一直在追尋的
an important direction
重要的一個方向
Then today I may try to share with you why this topic is very
那今天也許試圖來跟大家分享一下為什麼這個題目非常
very interesting very challenging
非常有趣 非常挑戰性
So how can we gain some new understanding of physics
那怎麼樣我們可以得到一些新的物理的了解
So here's what I'm talking about today
那在這裡我今天講的內容
The main thing is to talk first, of course talk a little bit
主要就是先是講 當然講一些
What exactly is directed? What does it mean?
到底什麼是操導的 什麼意思
It may be more than you imagine
那可能可以比大家想像的
And a little more strange phenomenon
還要更多一點奇特的現象
with some of its mechanics is very simple
跟它的一些機制很簡單的
Why do we have so many strange phenomena
為什麼我們會有那麼多奇怪的現象
But if you know something about this
但如果對這個有些了解
you can imagine what it does
就可以想像出來它到底有什麼作用
You may hear more about this
這個可能大家聽得會比較多一點
That is the aspect of the possible application of the steering material
那就是到底操導材料可能的應用的方面
that's been done a lot
那已經很多都在做了
The other one, of course, is what Wang Fuyuan said just now.
那另外一個當然就是最新剛才王復原長講的
The discovery of this high-temperature conductor
這個高溫操導體的發現
Near the end of 1986
將近1986年底
almost 30 years now
到現在已經將近30年
the discovery of this
這個的發現
a lot of confusion
產生的很多的困惑
that's confusing we're still trying to understand
那在困惑我們還在努力了解
don't already have quite a few close
不已經有相當多的接近
To understand the cause of this problem
要了解這個問題的原因
With the source of this tide island
跟這個潮島的來源
Well we just discovered a lot
那我們剛剛發現很多
It's not the same as the old tide island
跟以前的潮島不太一樣
Then of course the next step is
那這個當然下面一步就是
How to find higher tide temperature
怎麼找尋更高潮的溫度
Then of course why seek this
那當然為什麼要找尋這個
I have quite a big idea with this
跟這個就有相當大的觀念
OK, let's talk about this tide island phenomenon
OK 那我們來講一下這個潮島現象
Of course, the English name of this Superconductor is Superconductor
當然這個Superconductor的英文叫Superconductor
Calling this name, of course, ordinary people will think of it as one.
叫這個名字當然普通人都會想成一個
This English conductor has several opinions
這個英文的conductor是有幾個意見
One is the conductor and the other is the length of the vehicle
一個是導體 一個是這個車長
If the conductor of the train is also called conductor
如果列車的車長也叫conductor
The other one is the conductor, the conductor of the orchestra.
還有一個就是指揮 樂團的指揮
Then this Super is of course Superman
那這個Super當然是Superman
This Superconductor is what it means
這個Superconductor就是這個意思
Then there is another kind of Taiwan that everyone is more familiar with.
那還有一種大家比較熟悉的台灣
Well done called Semiconductor
做得很好叫半導體Semiconductor
there is a comic
那这里有个漫画
Let’s say this conductor only has work part time
就说这个conductor只有work part time
So it is semiconductor
所以它是semiconductor
Of course with SumSent is also right
当然与SumSent也对了
This semiconductor will see its resistance later
这个semiconductor等下会看到它的电阻
part of it is like conducting
就有一部分是像是conducting
sometimes not like
有些时候不像
So it is a general semiconductor
所以它是一般的semiconductor
the name goes
这个名字去
Then this superconductor
那这个superconductor
when he takes a good name
当他取的名字很好
Dangdang doesn't sound very familiar
当当听起来不是很了解
what does super mean
什么叫super的意思
what about this gentleman
那这位先生呢
is honest
是honest
this is dutch
这是荷兰人
At the University of Leiden
在University of Leiden
in 1911
1911年的时候
about 100 years ago
大概将近100多年以前
In 1911, he conducted an experiment
1911年时候他做了一个实验
Of course he wasn't
当初他当然不是
especially to find
特别就要去找
This super early experiment
这个超早的实验
this is a resistor
这个是电阻
let me explain
等一下我来解释
What does this resistor mean?
这个电阻到底什么意思这样
This is the resistance represented by the OMU
这是电阻用OMU来表示
Its special experiment is that it can reduce the temperature to a very low
它做的特别的实验是它把温度可以降到很低
It is a liquid state, but it turns into a liquid state at 4.2 degrees
就是液态害,但是4.2度才变成液态
Above 4.2 degrees it is gaseous
超过4.2度它就是气态
It can make liquid damage
它能够做出液态害来
that is its most important job
那个是它最重要的工作
After this work it is done
这个工作它做了以后
It puts some metals and other things in the low temperature to see
它就把一些金属等等的东西都放在低温里面去看
what happened
发生什么事情
This approach is often a scientific approach
这种做法这是常常科学的一种做法
It's just going to a place that no one else has been to.
就是去人家没有去过的地方
See questions that people have never seen before
去看人家从来没看过的问题
Of course the problem is the low temperature
当然这个问题就是低温
Occurs at very low temperatures
在很低温的下面发生
Of course, low temperature is very important now.
当然现在低温是非常重要的Industry
This whole is under low temperature and it goes to measure
这个整个在低温之下它去量
It this resistance of course from high temperature
它这个电阻当然从高温
This 270 degrees can be 273 degrees
这个270度可以是273度
So this is about 269 degrees
所以这个大概是269度
Just -269 degrees facility
就-269度设施
Zero degrees at our facility is
我们设施的零度是
273 degrees absolute
絕對溫度的273度
This is the absolute temperature
這是絕對溫度
So you are now saying that from this room temperature all the way down
所以你現在就說從這個室溫一直往下
You're going to get down to about 300 degrees
你要降到300度左右
you can get to this temperature
你才能到這個溫度
Absolute temperature below 0 degrees is no temperature
絕對溫度0度以下是沒有溫度的
This temperature has an absolute value
這個溫度有一個絕對值
is 0 degrees
是0度
it keeps cooling
它一直降溫度
Then watch the resistor drop all the way down
然後看這個電阻一直往下掉
to here
到這裡
suddenly fell fast
忽然之間掉得很快
down to 3 orders of magnitude 4 orders of magnitude
掉到3個數量級 4個數量級
Negatives from here to 10
從這裡到10的負物
fall here
掉到這裡
then 4.15 degrees
然後4.15度
It can be seen here that 4.2 degrees
這裡看得出來4.2度
just too high
剛好比一太high
a little lower temperature
低一點點溫度
So too high is very important
所以一太high很重要
put it in
一放進去
it's lower
它低一點
Eh
诶
it got
它得到了
this phenomenon
這個現象
this is
這個就是
superconducting
超導
found for the first time
第一次被發現
This is 1911
這個是1911年
You will probably see this picture many times
這篇圖你大概會看很多次
this is
這個是
This temperature is called the part temperature Tc
這個溫度我們叫做零件溫度Tc
C is
C就是
English is called Critical Temperature
英文叫Critical Temperature
is the part temperature
就是零件溫度
The Tc I used in this talk is the representative
我在這個talk裡面用的Tc就是代表
just go from normal to super old temperature
就從正常態變成超老態的溫度
What we are looking for is to increase the temperature
我們要尋找高溫的就是把這個溫度提高
best to mention room temperature
最好提到室溫
this is everyone's dream
這個是大家的夢想
Of course it is asking why
當然是問為什麼用
This zero resistance is of course here you see
這個零電阻當然在這裡你看到
Its resistance is not zero
它電阻並不是零
It is also a real parent, a real mother
它也是實的父母 實放母母
Just good resistance
只是電阻滿好的
not exactly zero
也並不是完全是零
How do we know this is zero resistance
我們怎麼曉得這個是零電阻
After this material comes out
這個材料出來以後
Of course it slowly started to become popular in cryogenics
當然很慢慢開始低溫物裡變得很流行
so many people do
所以很多人做
it is
它是
Then from just now what it does is mercury
然後從剛才它做的是水銀
is the arch
是拱
then there is lead
然後有鉛
These materials one by one
這些材料一個一個
Then first do single-atom metals in the periodic table
然後先做單原子的金屬在周期表裡
Then do the bimetallic
然後再做雙金屬
alloy of two elements
兩種元素的合金
do it
做上去
do here almost
做到這裡差不多
almost
差不多
Then later do three elements
然後後來又做三種元素
you can tell
你可以看出來
The physicist starts from the simplest kind of element
這物理學家從最簡單的一種元素
Then do two more elements
然後再做兩種元素
make three elements
做三種元素
start looking for
開始一直去找
Say the superconducting temperature
說這個超導的溫度
So doing here is actually the highest at that time
那做到這裡其實是那時候最高
23 degrees
23度
I was doing a postdoc at the time
那時候我是正在做博士後
I'll study this when I do
我做到那時候就研究這個
Why is the superconducting temperature 23 degrees?
為什麼超導溫度是23度
Back then I called it a high temperature superconductor
那時候我把它叫做高溫超導體
Of course it looks funny now
那現在看起來當然很好笑
That's only 23 degrees absolute temperature
那才絕對溫度23度而已
At that time, this material was also difficult to make.
那那個時候這個材料也很難做
Only one group can make it
只有一個group可以做出來
that is a world record
那是世界紀錄
back then i remember in ganis
那時候在我記得在Ganis
It is also written in the world record
那個世界紀錄裡面還寫下
This is the world's highest temperature superconductor
這個是世界最高的溫度的超導體
23 degrees
23度
that's a big deal
那已經不得了
then this is
那這個是
After that, of course, new materials started to come out.
那後來當然又開始有新的材料出來
but it's too late
但這個是已經很晚了
At that time in 1970
那個時候1970年
At that time we were the earth
那時候我們是大地
The material is also interesting
這個材料也很有趣
but at that time
但是在那個時候
Everyone do this temperature
大家就做到这个温度
This was 4 years ago in 2011
这个在2011年4年以前
This is a British magazine
这是英国的一个杂志
journal of physics
物理杂志
published a special issue
就出了一本专刊讲
100 Years of Drilling Development
100年来的操导的发展
just said
刚才讲的
The words developed in the past 100 years
这100年来发展的话
Of course there are some
这当然有一些就是
Nuo Biao said it was related to this drill
诺表讲跟这个操导有关的
In fact, the first person is of course
其实这个第一个人当然是
It's that Mr. Ones just now
就是刚才那位Ones先生
campman
Campman
Now at University Leiden
现在在University Leiden
There is a Museum
有一个Museum
If you go to University Leiden
如果你们去University Leiden
that is very old
那是个很老
300+ Years of University
300多年的大学
There is a laboratory in that university
那个大学里面有一个实验室
There is this Museum
有这个Museum
dedicated to his cryogenic laboratory
专门是他的低温实验室
That is the most famous cryogenic laboratory in the world
那个是世界上最有名的低温实验室
He spoke with a promise
他拿诺表讲
In fact, it is not because of the discovery of the manipulation
其实不是因为发现操导
It's because he lowered the temperature to one too high
是因为他把温度降到一太嗨
this is
这个是
Sorry I didn't translate
抱歉 我没翻译
This is the original promise
这个是当初诺表
Citation when Community gave him a promise
Community给他诺表讲的时候的Citation
not about coaching
不是讲操导
Because at that time, I didn't understand manipulation at all.
因为那时候根本不了解操导
Back then there was no quantum physics
那时候也没有量子物理才开始
I don't know what that means
不懂这什么意思
wait a minute and you'll think about it
等一下你们就想着
so don't appreciate at all
所以根本不appreciate
And at that time, they were also speculating on the teacher's parents
而且那时候也在炒师的父母
Sifang shopkeeper is not a spirit
四方店主也不是灵
what's special
有什么特别
There are of course many explanations for this
那这个当然有很多种解释
So this is probably when
所以这个大概是那时候
But in 1972 this paper
但1972年这篇paper
Of course it is a theoretical paper
当然是理论的paper
explains the phenomenon of manipulation
解释了操导的现象
This is written by water
这个是water写
after this comes out
这个出来以后
The overall understanding of manipulation is greatly increased
整个对操导的了解是极具的增加
That's an important theory
那这个是重要的一个理论
a breakthrough theory
一个突破性的理论
So it's actually the same as the discovery of the God Particle
所以其实跟发现上帝粒子
everything matters
什么都有关系
This theory has far-reaching
这个理论是远远的影响了
Many developments in high-energy particle physics
很多高能物理粒子物理的发展
the two
那这个两位
Even three of them are also physicists
就是三位也是物理学家
Same County NOW WebPly 1973
同县NOW WebPly的1973年
I also saw some manipulative phenomena
也是看到一些在操导现象的
special phenomenon
特别的现象
Of course I won't talk about this, just 90 points a piece
這個我當然不會講就90分一塊
One of the books that this gentleman gave is that he is doing a Ph.D.
這位先生他拿講的一個著作是他在做博士
Dissertation written during PhD studentship
念博士生的時候寫的論文
His teacher is a very famous physicist
他的老師是非常有名的物理學家
A question came up during class
上課的時候講到一個問題
Said the question is very interesting
說這個問題很有興趣
do it and see what happens
做一做看看有什麼結果
He just did it and made a promise
他就去做了做了就拿諾表講
This is the simplest paper I have ever seen
這個是我從來沒見過最簡單的一篇paper
Of course he has great consequence
當然他有很大的consequence
These are the two who discovered high temperature very early in 1987
這個是1987發現高溫超早的兩位
Bennel's Swiss and German Mueller
Bennel的瑞士人跟德國人Mueller
Take the promise
拿的諾表講
Three more in 2003 with two Russians
2003年又有三位有兩位俄國人
Because the American professor took the promise
因為美國教授拿的諾表講
it's all about theory
這都跟理論有關
So there are two related to the theory
所以有兩個是跟理論有關
out of twelve
十二個人裡面
Ten are related to experiments
十個是跟實驗有關的
wait some people i will mention
等一下有些人我會提到
not all
不是所有的
First we have to remind
首先我們要提醒一下
Because everyone may go to college for a long time
因為大家可能很久上大學
Probably a long time ago or in high school what is a resistor
可能很久以前是或者高中什么是电阻
Let's take a look at what zero resistance means
我们再来看看什么是零电阻的意思
Resistors are actually very simple
电阻其实很简单
take a material
就拿一个材料
Then you add a direct current like
然后你就加一个直流电一样
add a battery
加一个电池
Current flows from positive to negative
有电流就会通过正电流到负电
That's what we both said
那个就是我们俩的话
Just put a Ford battery
就是放了一个福特的电池
Then how many tenths of an ampere do I have
然后我有多少个零点二个安培的电流
I divide it and I am my resistor
我除一下我就是我的电阻
That resistance is just ohms
那电阻就是刚才的欧姆
But this is of course a bit simple
可是这个当然是有一点简单
because this thing has a problem
因为这个东西有一个问题
Let's say that if the length becomes longer
就说假如说这个长度变长
If say the length of this conductor is doubled
如果说这个导体的长度增加一倍
Then of course we are as small as water
那我们当然小的跟水流一样
if you manage to double
如果你管着长一倍
your flow is reduced by half
你的水流就少一半
Cut the current in half
电流减一半
then you double the resistance
那你的电阻就加倍
because you cut this in half
因为你把这个变一半
If the entire value remains unchanged
那整个value就这个不变的话
you just doubled
你就是增加了一倍
this resistor
這個電阻
Then if you take this area
那你如果把這個面積
double doubled
double增加一倍
then the current doubles
那電流就加倍
we all know that
這我們都曉得
If the tube is doubled
如果把管子加大一倍
the flow of water doubles it
水流讓它增加一倍
Then the resistance is reduced by half
那這個電阻就減少一半
So the resistor itself acts as a
那所以這個電阻本身當作是
It depends on the length and area of ​​the material
看你是材料的長度跟結面積
It will be different if you measure it
你量出來都會不一樣
Although both take the same line
雖然同樣都拿同線
coarse wire fine wire
粗的同線 細的同線
length you will get different
長短你都會得到不一樣的
so it's not a good number
所以這不是一個很好的數字
because it will experiment with everyone
因為它會隨著每個人做實驗
The amount of this material is different
量的這個材料不一樣
Although the same
雖然是同一個同
but you will measure the difference
但是你會量出來不同的
because this
因為這個
So use a resistivity
所以就用一個電阻率
Using resistivity is not equal to
用電阻率就是不等於
It is only a negative film as a material
它只底片當材料
so everything
所以每一樣東西
if you check now
如果你現在上去查
just check everything
就查到每一個東西
arch gold copper silver
拱 金 銅 銀
have a certain resistivity at room temperature
都有一定的電阻率在室溫的時候
Then this is a table
那這個是一個table
everyone this is
大家這個就是
If Ohm's Law
如果是歐穆定律的話
Then this is electricity
那這個是電
it's easy
就很简单了
just like the flow of water
就是跟水流一样
Water press
加水压机
then you have flow
然后你就有水流
And then you just viscosity it
然后你就它的Viscosity
This is called a resistor here
这这里就叫做电阻
Then if you are in an ideal body
那如果你在一个理想的经体中
I take this at this time
我这个时候拿这个
A Nature Physics cover that came out to draw the cover
出来画封面的一个Nature Physics封面
draw this beautifully
把这个画得很漂亮
these atoms
这些原子
Different sizes represent different atoms
不同大小就是代表不同的原子
Ranked seventy-seven
排得整整七七
This is our hypothetical ideal body
这是我们假想最理想的经体
Every atom is in its rightful place
每一个原子都排在它应有的位置
A very regular structure arranged neatly
一个很规则的结构排列整齐
where are you high
那你在那这个高
Plus it's a superconductor
另外这是一个超导体
It's the same as the blue back
就是蓝背同样
This is Wu Maokun Su Jingwu
这就是吴茂坤 苏靖五
this was done
这个当初做的
This is the Nano watch award
这个是纳诺表奖
No they're the one Bandle Mueller found
不是他们是Bandle Mueller找到的一个
This is what you see neatly arranged
这个也是你看排的整整齐
if you imagine this is this
如果你想象这个就是这个的话
These atoms are
这些原子就是这样
it lined up the whole
它就排的整个
The body is very structured
经体是非常有结构的
Then under such words
那在这样之下的话
of course you can ask
你当然可以问
Where do I get the resistors?
那我哪來的電阻
In fact, there is no resistance
其實上是沒電阻
If your resistor
如果你這種電阻
If it is very powerful
如果是非常厲害
It's all the same
都是看剛才一樣
You won't have resistors anymore
你不會有電阻了
So everyone thought of it before
那所以大家以前就想到
you may not have a resistor
你可能沒有電阻
the so-called resistance
那所謂電阻
The possible reason everyone thinks
可能來的原因大家就想
that must be out of alignment
那一定是排列不整齊
One of the reasons is right
這其中一個原因是沒錯
if you these
如果你這些
position of some atoms
有些原子的位置
not your usual
不是照你通常的
If this position is placed
這個位置在擺的話
The position of the pendulum
該擺的位置
it went sideways a bit
它走了旁邊一點
a little to the right
右邊一點
There is an extra charge in the hole
空穴裡面多了一個電
atom
原子
Then when your electrons are running
那你電子在跑的時候
will collide
就會碰到碰撞
Just like everyone sitting here
就跟這裡大家坐著一樣
sit well
坐得好好的
then if you have to go through
那如果要經過
If there is no middle
中間沒有走到的話
Everyone sit well
大家坐得排還好
Then if there are a few people crooked
那要如果有幾個人歪來歪去
Then it will be difficult for you to leave
那你要走就很困難了
you will hit
你就會撞到
Then when you hit this electron
那你撞到這個電子的時候
you will have resistance
你就會有電阻
This is where the main resistance comes from
這就是主要的電阻的來源
It is because of the flash of impurities
是因為有雜質的閃射
Of course, a piece as big as the body
當然經體那麼大的一塊
The body is one centimeter in length, width and height
經體一個公分長寬高的
But if it is not perfect, you will have this problem
但是如果不是perfect,你就会有这个问题
This is one of the main sources of resistance.
这个就是主要电阻来源的之一了
This is what everyone probably knew before
这个是大家可能以前就知道
I'm just talking about the previous resistance problem that reminds everyone
我只是讲一讲让大家想起来的以前的电阻问题
Every time this resistor hits
每次这个电阻撞击的时候
In fact, it will make this atom move
其实就会让这个原子也动
so energy is lost
所以就会损失能量
This is why there is energy when there is resistance
这就是为什么有电阻就会有能量
That's what we have in this resistor problem
这就是我们在这个电阻的问题里面的问题
Why is there heat when there is resistance?
为什么有电阻就会有热
all computers are
所有的电脑就是
Most of the heat in all computers is due to the resistance born
所有的电脑的大部分的热的来源都是因为电阻出生
That is, what we are moistening are all resistances.
就是我们在润的都是电阻常生的
So most of the heat comes out of the resistor
所以大部分的热都是从电阻出来的
all electronic everything
所有的电子一切
this is one of the factors
这个是其中一个因素
Of course there is another factor
当然还有一个因素是
It's that you arrange these atoms neatly
就是你排的整整齐齐这些原子
They were also disturbed to break up and sat there huddled
他们也不安分手挤的坐在那里不动
It's not like everyone here is doing a good job listening
不像各位在这里听都做得好好的
But after a while you probably don't want to move
但是过一阵你可能也不想要动一阵
Move your hands, move your feet, move your head
手動一下 腳動一下 頭動一下
It also moves on this principle
這個原則它也要動
And the reason it moves is of course related to quantum mechanics
而且它動的原因是當然跟量子力學有關
A characteristic of quantum mechanics is that
量子力學的一個特點就是
The more motionless you are, the higher your energy will be
你如果越不動 你的能量就越高
The more you have to expand your range of motion
你越要擴大你的動的範圍
In fact, the lower the energy
其實能量是越低
This is the Uncertainty Principle of Quantum Mechanics
這是量子力學的這個叫海參堡不確定原理
you may have heard it before
大家可能以前聽過
this is related to this
這個是跟這個有關
So atoms even at absolute zero temperature
所以原子即使在絕臉溫度零度
Atoms can still move, it is impossible to stay still
原子還是會動 不可能不動
this thing is troublesome
這個東西就麻煩
When it moves, you, the electron, are running
它這個一動 你這個電子在跑的時候
will bump into
就會撞來撞去
Because of it, you were good at first, and everyone took a pat to do it well.
因為它 你本來是好好的大家一拍拍做好
You now hit like this atom passing by
你現在像這個原子經過就撞到了
atoms hit
原子一經過撞到
Especially if you're going from one end to the other
尤其你要經過是從一頭走到另一頭
The distance on the other end is
另外一頭這個的距離是
Usually we say that less than one is unavoidable
通常我們講就是小於一個難免
This distance is less than one nanometer
這個距離都是小於一個耐米
But you have to go from one end of the electron to the other end by walking 10 to the 7th power of Naimi
但是你從這頭電子要走到那頭是走10的7次方的耐米
It is 7 orders of magnitude of rice
就是7個數量級的耐米
That's 10 million times
就是1000萬次的話
Then of course you have a very high chance of colliding.
那你當然要撞的機率非常大
bump bump bump bump bump
撞來撞去撞來撞去
The current becomes very small
一下就電流就變得很小了
Not many pass
通過的不多
That's a lot of heat
那熱量就很大了
So this is also a
所以這個也是一個
I just said half of what I just said about semiconductors.
那剛才講的半導體就說我說一半
You see it looks like metal when it's hot
你看它像金屬在高溫的時候
Acts like an insulator at low temperatures
低溫的時候就像絕緣體
this is semiconductor
這就是半導體
It's just that it only works for half a day.
就是它只上半天的班好
then stop
然後就不上了
The metal is completely different.
那這個金屬的話就完全不一樣
But the colder it is, the lower its resistance
但越低溫它的電阻就越低
This has a feature
這有一個特性
but when it won't go to zero
但是當它不會到零
There is a problem with this
這樣子的話是有問題的
The performance of this is to say
那這個的表現就是說
It is a characteristic of metal
它一個是金屬的特性
The characteristics of that semiconductor
那個半導體的特性
If it is an insulator, it will run up from the beginning
絕緣體的話一開始就往上跑
It just looks like there's no resistance and it's very high
就看起來就沒有電阻就非常高
That's another reason
那這個是另外一個原因
the atom itself
就是這個本身原子
That is, you have grown a very good body
就是你長出非常好的經體
That atom is not very safe
那原子也不是很安分的
Then this will also cause resistance
那這個也會造成電阻
There is another one, of course
那還有一個當然是
The problem with electrons is that they all carry a charge
電子有一個麻煩是大家都帶電荷
same charge
同樣的電荷
We all know that like charges repel each other.
那大家曉得同電荷是互相排斥的
cool wheel force
酷輪作用力
Everyone remembers this
這個大家都記得
Then of course the cool wheel force can cause problems too.
那這酷輪作用力當然也會造成問題
Then your electron will hit you as soon as you move.
那你這個電子一動就會撞到
This cool wheel force affects the battery next door
這個酷輪作用力就影響到隔壁的電池
next to the battery
旁邊的電池
all will be affected
統統都會被影響
if you go astray
那你如果你走歪
you should have gone like this
你本來該這樣走了
Everyone should go like this
大家都要這樣子走
when the current flows
那個電流過的時候
we all want to go together
大家都想一起走
you come across this EY
你碰到這個EY
you will hit other
你就會撞到其他的
hit hit hit hit
一撞到撞到撞到
hit a lot of electrons
就撞了很多個電子
Then the whole scattering is very troublesome
那整個scattering就很麻煩了
becomes a very fast loss of energy
就變成損耗能量非常快
Then the current becomes smaller
那這個電流就變小
It hit a lot of water pipes
就跟水管裡面撞了一大堆
something other than water flowing past
其他的東西不是水流過去
will hit
都會撞到
your miscosy gets bigger
你的 miscosy 就變很大
the same principle
這個同樣的原理
So the main thing I'm talking about here is these factors.
所以這裡這套神電阻我講的主要的就是這幾個因素
This problem is what I just said about resistors.
這個問題就剛才我講電阻的
just said it was mentioned
就說有提到這個問題
Is this resistor really 0?
這個電阻真的是0嗎?
10 negative quad ohms
10的負四方歐姆
You say you look small when measured
你說你量起來看起來是蠻小的
If you change what I just said today
你如果今天換剛才我講的
Change your same material to increase the section area
換你同樣的材料把節面積變大
Isn't the resistance half
電阻不是一半嘛
then you're smaller again
那你就又更小了
Then if you make this material longer
那你如果把這個材料變長一點
double the resistance
電阻又升一倍
right
對不對
That means you are 0 or not 0
那就是說你到底是0不是0
If it is 0, how can I width and length
如果0的話我怎麼寬長
it should all be 0
它都應該是0
So are you really 0?
那你這個是不是真的0?
Or your equipment is not very good
還是你的儀器不太好
Of course in 1911 I don't think the instruments are very good
當然1911年我想儀器都不太好了
we all know
我們都曉得
This is far from now
這個離現在差很遠
Is the small 0 of water really 0?
水小的0是不是真的0?
So why not 0.00001?
那為什麼不是0.00001呢?
plus a 0
再加一個0
10-6 is 0
10-6是0
that's not 0
那还不是0
So this topic is kind of interesting
所以这个题目是有点有趣的
is what is called 0
就是什么叫做0
Certainly a very special concept
当然是一个很特别的观念
i remember where i read
我记得我才哪里读过
0 Chinese people did not have 0 at the beginning
0 中国人一开始是没有0的
It seems that there is no 0 in Chinese numbers.
好像中国人的数字里面是没有0的
When it hits 0, it jumps over
碰到0就把它跳过去
We have negative certificates but no 0
我们有负的证的 但是没有0
But it seems that a mathematician in India invented
但是好像是印度的一位数学家发明
it's a bold move
这是一个大胆的动作
This proxy is really 0
这个代理是说真的是0
the question of course
这个问题当然
someone will bring it up soon
马上就有人提出来
you see this you say 0
你看到这个 你说是0
So he didn't dare to say 0 o'clock
所以他也不敢讲0点
His name is supercanda
他叫supercanda
he got a good name
他这个名字取得很好
called super
叫super
Not small things call it super
不小的东西都把它叫super
Probably a very good idea
大概是a very good idea
this is a good thing
这个是一个好的事情
so he called super
所以他叫超
This is English, this word is very useful
这个是英文这个字很有用
Of course, there will be a challenge immediately
这个到底当然马上就有人challenge
Better Instruments More Accurate Measurements
更好的儀器 更精準的測量
can i get this
我能不能得到這個
How to do it?
那怎麼做呢?
then they say
那他們說
if we just said
如果我們剛才講了
voltage equals current times resistance
電壓等於電流乘上電阻
right? everyone has learned this
對不對?大家都學過這個
If you say this thing is equal to 0
如果你說這個東西等於0
If there is a thing
那假如有一個東西
The right side here is equal to 0
這邊右邊等於0
Of course, the left side must be equal to 0
當然左邊要等於0
That means I didn't add the battery
就是說我沒有加電池
I can also have current
我也可以有電流
How is that?
那怎麼是呢?
Let's say you start by adding a little bit of voltage
假如說你先開始加一點點電壓
Let the current start to run and then exceed
讓它電流開始跑了再超到
Then you take the battery away
然後你就把電瓶拿走
most of the material
大部分的材料
If you do this the battery will die immediately
如果你做這個馬上就沒電了
you can measure
你可以量
Everyone knows that there will be no current
大家都曉得馬上就沒電流了
If you take the usual conductor
如果你把平常的導體
you do this
你去做這個事情
the current will be back soon
電流馬上回來
Then they did this experiment
那他們就做了這個實驗
take it away
把它拿走
just let the current run
就讓這個電流開始跑
As soon as it runs it takes the battery away
一跑它就把電瓶拿走
then watch
然後就看
When will this current disappear
什麼時候這個電流會消失掉
This is a good TES
這個很好的TES
If you have resistance
你如果有電阻
it's gone
一下就沒了
Then they went for more than a year
那他們走了一年多
This is really an experiment
這個是真的有做這個實驗
more than a year
做了一年多
This current is almost
這個電流幾乎沒
Of course they can't wait any longer
當然他們再等不下去了
It is also difficult to write paper
要寫paper也很難了
Even a little bit is fine
就算了一點都可以了
almost you are small
差不多你算起來就很小了
It means there is little resistance
就表示有電阻也很小
The current estimate is 10-2
現在當中的estimate是10-2
Is its square ohm meter
是其方ohm meter
is resistivity
是電阻率的
Of course this is the best instrument
當然這個是最好的儀器
may be this orum
可能是這個orum
In fact the result
事實上這個結果
then very important
然後很重要
it is not 0.0001
它不是0.0001
It is likely to be exactly 0
它很可能就是exactly 0
this is interesting
這個就有趣了
because most things
因為大部分的東西
We learn things like
我們學到像這樣子的東西
you have many decimal points
你都有很多小數點
you can take 10-6
你可以拿10-6
What - 100 times
什麼-100次
Just -100 is not 0
只是-100也還不是0
How do you say it is exactly 0
你要怎麼樣講說是exactly 0
this is an interesting question
這是一個有趣的問題
we have words for each of you
我們有各位各數的話
It's easy to say 0
就很容易講0
If we are 1 2 3
我們如果是1 2 3
we say one person two people
我們說有一個人兩個人
You can say that the 0 people are no one in the room
你就可以說,那0個人就是房間裡沒人
Of course then I thought there was a problem
當然後來我想到有個麻煩
Someone comes in with one foot, do you want to count it as 0.3 people
有人身一隻腳進來,你要不要算0.3個人
it's a bit of a hassle
這有點麻煩
But if you use him to count, you will say 1, 2, 3
但是如果把他用各數算,你就會講1、2、3
-1-2, 0 is very simple
-1-2、0就很簡單
But what if you want to count by 10, 0.001, 0.001, 0.001?
但如果你要10數,0.001、0.001、0.001怎麼辦?
This reminds me of the Sanju Qing'an in Taiwan a while ago
這就我想起來,台灣前一陣子的那個三聚清安
If you want to subtract 0, it will be troublesome. What is 0 minus?
說要0減出,就麻煩了,什麼叫0減出?
This obviously depends a lot on what instrument you're using.
這個顯然非常看你用什麼儀器
It's just that the equipment I just mentioned is a bit rotten.
就是我剛才講的儀器爛一點
You subtract everything from 0, because you can't measure anything
你像什麼都是0減出,因為什麼都測不到
But if you use a good instrument, nothing is 0 minus
但你如果用很好儀器,什麼都不是0減出
because there is something to see
因為什麼看都有東西
So this thing is here, and this is the same
所以這個東西就在這裡,這個也同樣的
This question is of course a long time quarrel, isn't it exactly 0?
這個問題當然是爭吵很久,是不是exactly 0?
But what I'm talking about here is that this is the real 0
但我這裡講的是,這個是真正的0
exactly 0, mathematically you can say it is precisely
exactly 0,數學上你可以說它是precisely
not that almost
也不是說幾乎有
or not there is or there is not
或沒有 那有就是沒有
It only has one or no resistance or no resistance
它只有有個沒有 有電阻或沒電阻
The one without resistance is exactly no resistance
那個沒電阻是exactly沒電阻
So this state is immediately small from this perspective.
所以這個態從這個角度講馬上就小的了
Because in physics we study classical physics
因為在物理裡面我們學古典物理
What variables and phenomena are continuous
什麼變數什麼現象都是連續性的
0.001 is fine, you look at 0.001
0.001好了 你再看0.001
Keep going, you measure more and more
繼續下去 你量得越整越多
decimal point but never exactly
小數點 但是永遠不會是exactly
but in quantum mechanics
但是在量子力學呢
everything is discrete
什麼東西都是離散式的
So when you see this you know
所以一看到這個你就曉得了
This state is beyond our classical understanding
這個態不是我們古典的了解的
state, the electron enters a new state
態 電子進入一個新的情況了
The electron suddenly changed
這個電子忽然之間變成變了
It becomes a product of a quantum
它變成在一個量子的一個產合了
it must be bright small
它一定是亮的小型
Otherwise it wouldn't be exacting
要不然的话它不会是exacting
only bright
只有是亮的
we are 1 2 3 0
我们是1 2 3 0
Now of course there are other examples
现在当然还有其他的例子
some other its conductance
有些别的它的电导
are called bright numbers
是叫做亮的数的
This is all because of the small size of the light
这个都是因为跟亮的小型有关
It is not an ordinary material
它这个不是平常的材料
you can see it
你看得到了
this is the first point
这个是第一点
it is bright small
它是亮的小型
At first this guide
当初这个操导
did not understand this
没有理解这一点
so didn't give that onus
所以没有给那个onus
Because of discovery manipulation
因为发现操导
This discovery is of course an extraordinary thing
这个发现当然是不得了的事情
for finding a new quantum
因为找到一个新的量子
of course at that time
当然在那个时候
We've only just begun with the mechanics of the light
我们对亮的力学完全才开始
don't understand at all
完全不理解
I don't even dare to say now
现在其实我也不敢说
Our understanding of the mechanics of light
我们对亮的力学理解
just we know how to use it
只是我们知道怎么用它
wait a minute we'll talk
等一下我们会讲
But it can have a definite
但是它可以有一个确定的
We know that it must be discrete
我们知道是它一定是要离散式的
discontinuity
非连续性
This is a characteristic of the leon phenomenon
这是亮子现象的一个特征
give it many other features
讓它有別的很多特徵
Like the uncertainty principle just mentioned, etc.
像剛才講的不確定原理等等
well-known phenomenon
大家都熟能知的現象
that this is a feature
那這個是一個特徵
is discrete
就是離散式的
it is not a continuum
它不是一個連續性的
Then everyone knows this very clearly, right?
那這個當了大家其實很清楚的就知道對不對
If you look at the periodic table
你如果看周期表
Did you learn the periodic table
你當初學過周期表
It is very hard to memorize this periodic table
要背這個周期表很辛苦
i can never get it back
我從來背不起來
But if the periodic table is here
不過這個周期表在這裡的話
You look carefully at every periodic table
你仔細看它每一個周期表
How does it define its atomic number
它就要怎麼定義它的原子數
It is like this is this Sodium
它就比如說這個是這個Sodium
Then its electron is an orbital
那它的這個電子是軌道
It's called ES2,2S2P6
它叫ES2,2S2P6
Then you see it is represented by numbers
那你看它都是用數字代表
very discreet
非常discreet的
Discrete
離散式的
it is not a continuous
它不是一個continuous
Nothing 0.99sqa
沒有什麼0.99sqa
it has a special track for everything
它每一件事都有一個特別的軌道
its orbit is discrete
它的軌道是離散
Then all these things are according to this card
那所有的这些东西都是照这个牌的
Of course, the real inside is a little richer than this.
当然真正的里面比这个还富大一点
But it is a discrete
但是它是一个离散式
It's very simple, it's an electron
这是很简单 这是一个电子
the one we just talked about
刚才我们讲的那个
The electrons in the conductor are 10 in the 23-foot room
在导体里面的电子是10的23尺房的
There are 10 to 23 electrons in a conductor of one centimeter or three centimeters
在一个公分 立体公分的导体里面有10的23分电子
But it is also discrete
但是它也是离散的
That is of course a very miraculous thing
那这个当然是一个很神奇的事情
This is just an example, the quantum mechanics that everyone is familiar with must be discrete
这个就是举个例 就是大家都熟悉的量子力学一定是离散的
This theory was solved in 1957
这个理论在1957年被解决了
They held it in 1973 and don't talk about it
他们1973年拿着不要讲
It is very surprising that this theory was proposed in 1957
1957年提出这个理论是非常令人惊讶的
because they solved the problem
因为他们解决了这个问题
Of course, many people do not get this question completely right.
当然很多人做这个问题都没有完全作对
they are totally right
他们是完全作对了
They not only explain the mechanism of superconductivity
他们不但解释超导机制
Also explains the quantum state of superconductivity
也解释了超导的量子态
The whole topic starts from using quantum physics to solve this problem
整個題目出發都是用量子物理來做這個問題
that can fully explain
那就完全能夠解釋
Of course it's amazing
當然這是很神奇的
amazing job
很了不起的工作
able to explain the problem
能夠把這個問題一次解釋
Of course there are a lot of new ideas coming from here
當然有很多新的想法從這裡面說
They don't even know they've done it themselves.
他們自己做完其實還不曉得
Some are amazing new ideas
有些是不得了的新的想法
This was of course understood later
這個後來當然被理解到
Let me explain their main theories a little bit today
他們主要的理論我今天來稍微解釋一下
Why does this mechanism exceed
就這個機制到底為什麼會超到
Electronics, we know that besides electric nuclear, there are optional
電子我們知道除了電核以外還有自選
Everyone says that electrons revolve around themselves
大家都說電子會自己繞著自己轉
In fact, of course, with a unique concept
其實當然是用獨點的觀念
Actually it has one thing
其實它就是有一樣東西
like optional
像叫做自選
it can have up or down
它可以有上或下
By or by or whatever you say
依或負以隨便你怎麼講
Anyway, there are two states
反正這有兩個態
it sometimes goes up and sometimes it goes down
它有時候上有時候下
This thing is powerful
這個東西是有實力舉的
So it can work in strength
所以它可以實力作用
Therefore, in addition to the energy expansion effect between electrons and electrons
所以電子跟電子之間除了擴能作用
In addition to this, it also has the effect of strength
這個以外它還有實力作用
There are also continuous words with atoms and ions
跟原子、離子這邊也有持續的話
it will all work
它都會有作用
Well here are some new
那這裡就是有一些新的
The characteristic of this theory is that
那這個理論的特點就是
They have a guy named Cooper
他們有一個人叫Cooper
Then CooperPay is pairing
那CooperPay 就是配對
Electronic pairing is called CooperPay
電子配對叫做CooperPay
is its most important job
就是它的最重要的工作
It states that electrons can form a pair
它指出來電子可以形成一個對
Especially these two electrons
尤其這兩個電子
Different choices can form a pair
自選不一樣可以形成一個對
This is a simple Picture that says
這個是一個簡單的Picture說
they will form a pair
他們會形成對
then of course you are weird
那你當然很奇怪
There is Kuren force in it
這裡面有庫人作用力
how does it come to form a pair
它怎麼來形成對
what makes it pair
什麼東西讓它形成對
because it clearly should exclude
因為它明明應該排斥的
then how does it pair
那它怎麼會配對
what about this pairing
那這個配對的情況是什麼
that question of course
那這個問題當然
They came up with a mechanism
他們想出來一個機制
of course proven
當然被證明了
Otherwise, I wouldn't be speaking outside
要不然也不會拿著外講
Experiments Many experiments have shown
實驗 很多實驗證明
The mechanism is actually quite simple
這個機制其實還蠻簡單的
From that point of view
從那個角度講
because we know
因為我們知道
In addition to the electrons in the meridian
經體裡面除了電子以外
You still have ions, right?
你還有離子對不對
shock drive
震駕
because its electrons run away
因為它的電子跑掉了
run around
跑去亂跑
have one or two electrons
有一個電子或兩個電子
don't follow this atom box
不跟著這個原子盒
it ran out by itself and wandered around
它自己跑出去到處亂晃
Its atomic box is of course the shock driver
它的原子盒當然就剩下是震駕
electron is attached
電子是附加
you atomic box
你這個原子盒
will again
又會
This ion will vibrate
這個離子會震盪
this is what we just said
這是我們剛剛講的
oscillate to oscillate
震盪來震盪去
So if you say you have a
那你如果說你有一個
Electrons go here first
電子先跑到這裡
Atom boxes next to these two
這兩個旁邊的原子盒
Because it's shocking
因為是震駕
see additional
看到附加
Of course they squeeze in
它們當然就向擠進去了
like
就像
if we have this here
如果我們這裡有這個
different gender
不同性別的
It's all about a woman
都是來一個女的
sit here
坐來這裡
come closer
來的就靠近一點
the role of this
這個的作用
created a little attraction
產生了一點點吸引力
this attraction
這個吸引力
Then when the two atomic boxes are close together
那這裡兩個原子盒靠近的時候
just a little bit more shocking
就比較震一點
because it appends
因為它一次附加
If those two are aligned
那兩個如果都正一架
These two add up to one more regular price
這兩個加起來就是又多了一個正價
The other electron also wants to join in the fun
那另外一個電子也想來湊熱鬧
between such mutual influences
就在這樣子互相的影響之間
on this principle
就這個原則
From another point of view, it is equal to these atomic boxes
從另外一個角度講就等於是這些原子盒
dug a hole
挖了一個洞
Those two electrons jumped in
那這兩個電子跳進去了
It's because of this atomic hole
就它因為這個原子會洞
So you electronic background
所以你這個電子來頭
it ran in one by two
它一兩個一跑進
Just take this potential
就把這個potential
This negative failed to increase
這個負的未能增加了
Negative fails to add another electron
負的未能增加另外一個電子
just saw again
就是又看到
have jumped in
有跳進去
So these two are starting to become each other
所以這兩個都開始互相變得在一起
attracting
在吸引
This is of course a very simple diagram.
這個當然是一個很簡單的示意圖了
This situation means that the child
那這樣子的情況就是表示這個生子
We call this child
這個我們叫生子
ion vibration
離子的振動
we call birth
我們叫生子
on sound transmission
就聲音傳播
your metal
你那個金屬
If you hit it, there will be a sound transmission
你打一下也會有個聲音傳播
That sound is transmitted by this vibration
那個聲音傳播就是靠這個振動
The vibration of this atom
這個原子的振動
Then this vibration is giving birth
那這個振動就是生子
Then this child is acting
那這個生子就是扮演
Eliminate a Glu combination
免一個Glu 聯合劑
just out of medicine
就是沒劑了
it comes here
它來這裡
grab these two
把這兩個就抓起來了
the two of them can be exchanged
他們兩個就可以交換
information can work
information 可以作用
If this is strong enough to dig the composition
如果這個夠強挖的構成
It's better if their repulsion isn't that strong.
他們的排斥力不夠那麼強就比較好
Of course, this fitting picture is drawn very small
當然這個試衣圖是畫得很小的
real time
真正的時候
The distance between these two pads can be quite far
這個兩個墊子距離可以滿遠的
If we each count as a round
如果我們每個都算一個圓子
If it fits
合的話
if you sit here
坐在這裡的話
These two cushions can be partitioned behind the wall
這兩個墊子可以隔到牆後面去了
this pair of electrons
這一對墊子
So the mat pairs in question are not necessarily the closest neighbors
所以講的墊子對不一定是最鄰近的
it can pad for a long distance
它可以很長距離的墊子
This can also cause this reaction
這個也是可以造成這個反應
Dara has a few special ones in it
Dara在裡面有幾個特別的
What it says is that the vibration of the rope is very important
它講的就是這個繩子的振動很重要
it will produce
它就會產生
if it doesn't work with the rope
如果它跟繩子沒有什麼作用的話
I said if these things can't move
我講如果這些東西都不能動
fix it there then it's gone
固定在那裡 那就沒有了
that doesn't need a guide
那也不需要操導
Because we can have perfect love
因為我們可以有perfect 愛
The ideal classic also has no resistance
理想經典也是沒有什麼電阻
But that one has no resistance
可是那個沒有電阻
It's a completely different mechanism than this
跟這個是完全不一樣的機制
this is there
這個是有
But it creates another situation
但是它會造成另外一個態勢
no resistance
沒有電阻
It goes from having a resistor to one without a resistor
它從有電阻會造成一個沒有電阻的
The most important thing is that it will form a CouplePet
最重要就是它會形成CouplePet
That's what CouplePet has
那有CouplePet有
So why is there no resistance?
那為什麼就變成沒有電阻呢?
This is what I found for a painting
這個就是我找了一個畫畫的
the russian painter
這位俄國的畫家
Drawings by Pervoninsky
Pervoninsky的畫畫
I think this is my favorite way to express
我覺得這個是我最喜歡來表示
The end electrons in the CouplePet pair
這個到底電子在CouplePet對
what to do in there
在裡面做什麼
Like so many people dancing Wars
就像那麼多人在跳Wars
waltz
華爾斯舞
in that hall
在那個大廳裡
you see so many people jumping
你看那麼多人跳
A man and a woman are making noise
一男一女鬧著轉
Then you can exchange pottener with each other
然後互相還可以交換Pottener
Exchange your Pay
交換你的Pay
can be exchanged
可以互相交換
How does he turn?
那他怎麼轉呢?
here again
這裡又有
There are flowers, chairs, tables, and pillars
有花啊,又有椅子,桌子,柱子
no problem
都沒問題
it keeps turning around
它一直可以轉來轉去
The whole weave jumps
整個圍織跳來
so you can imagine
所以你可以想像
Suppose there is such a beautiful
假設有這麼漂亮的
so many teams jumping over there
那麼多隊在那邊跳
how to dance
怎麼跳?
dancing to the music
順著音樂在跳
don't imagine each other
彼此不會想像
won't run into any obstacles
也不會撞到任何阻礙
What kind of pillars are the tables and chairs?
桌子椅子這些什麼柱子
just can go around
就是可以繞過去
no matter what
怎麼樣都不會撞到
and then exchange each other
然後互相可以交換
of these two
那這兩個當中
can't express it all
沒有辦法全部表達
Because the two of them are still close
因為他們兩個還是近距離
but you can imagine
但是你可以想像
some dancing
有的跳舞
We could have separated when we were kids
我們小時候可以手分開來的
two jump like this
兩個再這樣跳
then go over
然後再過去
jump like this
這樣子跳
then if you imagine
那你如果想像
In the current situation
像現在這樣子的情況的話
That's what all the electrons are doing
那所有電子都在做的
The electrons are divided one by one
那電子也分一來一
Well done
一紅好了
That is the last election
那就是上次選
Next time choose one to one red electron
下次選一來一紅的電子
Every electron can see
每個電子都可以看
it's one come one red
它是一來一紅
just jump each other once
就這樣一次跳互相
This is probably the most beautiful dancing episode
這是可能是最美的跳舞的情節
no matter how you dance
就不管怎麼跳
They are all very synchronized
他們都是非常的同步協調
then this is real
那這個是真正的
it's a huge amount
它是一个巨观的量
Why talk about macro
为什么讲巨观
Because it's not about an electron
因为它不是讲一个电子
two electrons
两个电子
real
实的
This 23rd power electron
这个23次方个电子
Tongtong is doing the same thing
通通在做同样一个事情
this is incredible
这个是不可思议的
This miracle of nature is
这个自然界的神奇是
far more than we think
远超过我们想想
how do you get all the electrons
你怎么把所有的电子
They all do this synchronous operation
都是做这么同步的运转
and won't install that episode
而且不会装那一期
so no electrons
所以没有电子
there are these pillars
有这些柱子
What table and chairs are there in the middle?
中间摆什么桌子椅子
also won't pretend
也一样不会装
It's all over
通通会了
These can also jump farther
这些还可以跳得更远距离
that's what i'm talking about here
就是我讲一个在这里
one there
一个在那里
how much are you right
你多少对
dance here
都在这里跳
So there are many pairs in between
所以中间有很多对
But I can still pair with that
但是我还是可以跟那个配对
you paired with that
你跟那个配对
jumping
互扬跳
But this is the closest I found
但这个是我找到最接近的
I can't find a better icon
我找不到更好的图示
if you go and close your eyes
如果你去把眼睛闭起来
think about this scenario
想想这个情景
Just thought this is so beautiful
就想到这个是美得不得了
This real physics is indeed very beautiful
這個真的物理確實是非常美麗
It's so hard to imagine
這個是多難想像出來
then they are not human
那他們又不是人
How can they be so harmonious
他們怎麼能做到這麼的和諧
such
這麼的
this is what i said
這個就是我講這句話
This coordination and harmony synchronize
這個協調和諧synchronize
this word is hard to come by
這個字是很難做得到
but they do it all
但是他們通通做到
So that means that every electron
所以那表示每一個電子
is actually doing the same thing for every electron
對 每一個電子其實都在做同樣的事情
Of course, we cannot tell the difference between electrons and electrons.
當然電子跟電子其實我們分不出來
people we can see
人我們看得出來
This man has a beard and no beard
這個人有鬍子沒鬍子
that just means
那只是意思
Of course you can't tell the difference
人家電子你當然分不出來
This is the electronics rack
這個是電子架
electronic handle
電子柄
of course not
那當然沒有了
Then all the electrons are like
那所有的電子都像是
Then of course all electrons do the same thing
那所有的電子當然都做一樣的事情
This is the real view. It's too good.
這個才是真正的俱觀量是太好
Then this can also be exchanged partners
那這個也可以交換同伴
Of course I won't say more now
當然我現在不講更多
It also goes in the opposite direction
它還要向相反方向
I just didn't say
我剛剛沒有說
I can't fix this picture
這張圖修不出來
you go ahead
你往前面走
This is your cooperation
這個你的配合也算是
go here mate, go here
往這裡同伴,往這裡走
if you go to the right, it goes to the left
如果你往右邊走,它就往左邊走
If you go backwards, it will go backwards
你往後走,它就它要往後走
walk in the opposite direction, all steps
走相反的方向,所有的步伐
So it's like dancing
所以這個跟跳舞很像
Because this pace is to match
因為這個步伐是要match
The console of the same nature doesn't like it
那同條性質的操導台不喜歡
Of course, because of this same article, it doesn't like it
當然,因為這個同條它就不喜歡
You will be paired to guess good, subject to different
你將配對猜善,受到不同地
Because as you can imagine, it dances so harmoniously
因為你可以想像,這麼跳得這麼和諧
If someone suddenly sees
如果有一個人忽然搬倒
That's terrible, many people next to me will follow suit
那慘了,旁邊很多人都要跟著搬倒
a lot is going to go wrong
一大堆就要出了問題
If someone goes to a dance buddy one hits the wall
如果有人去跳舞的夥伴一個撞到牆
The other one will be miserable
那另外一個就慘了
Someone next to me will hit the wall
那旁邊也有人會撞到牆
Creates a lot of matching at once , guess good
一下子就造成很多的配對,猜善
This is not a good thing, it will be lost
這個事不好,會損失
Just now I saw that one of them dug a trap
剛才剛才看它有一個挖了一個陷阱
Now if you want to guess Shan, there will be no more
那現在你如果要猜善就沒有了
there is no way
就沒有辦法
The other one is, if you say
那另外一個是,你假如說
The pair of blue and red in the middle is jumping
中間藍的跟紅的配對在跳
The blue ones are much more than the red ones, so how do you match them?
藍的比紅的多很多,那怎麼配對啊?
one question
一個問題
Difficult to match even if the numbers are different
數目不一樣也很難配對
how to become a guide
那要怎麼變成操導
So both of these will cause manipulation
所以這兩個都會造成操導的
unstable attitude
態度不穩定
Then this is of course the CooperPair
那這個是當然就是把這個CooperPair
broke it apart
把它拆散了
That's because it's too much
那這個是說因為這個太多
CooperPair has an up and a down
CooperPair都有一個上一個下
There are a lot more up than down.
那上的比下多很多就有很多
no right
沒有對
dancing alone
獨自一個人在跳
Of course it is not possible
那當然不是能夠很
performance evenly
均勻的在表現
In fact, this thing is an external magnetic field
那事實上這個事情就是外加磁場
will cause the phenomenon
會造成的現象
Because the electron I just mentioned has
因為剛才我講的這個電子有
self-taught backspin
自學下旋
it is magnetic
它是有磁性的
So the magnetic field will affect it
所以磁場會對它影響
The influence of the magnetic field will cause these things
那磁場的影響就會造成這些事情
then this is what we are now
那這個就是我們現在
Let's do some experiments for you
下面要來給大家做一些實驗
This is the magnetic field you see
這個就是大家看到的磁幅
Why is there a magnetic field
為什麼會有磁幅
In fact, it has a lot to do with this
其實跟這個太是有非常大的關係
Because this is why it prefers Chen Taitai
因為這個是它比較喜歡陳代太
If a magnetic field is forced to be applied, what kind of phenomenon will it produce?
硬要加磁场,它会产生什么样的现象
Just because it doesn't like this, so it does weird things
就是因为它不喜欢这个,所以它做了很奇怪的事情
shall we do this demonstration
我们是不是来做一下这个示范
Of course this will burn, 77 degrees is very cold
这个当然会烧伤的,这77度是很冷的
If you take a small piece of metal, it'll all sit in there, and it'll become brittle
你如果拿一小片金属,它都会放在里面以后,它就会变脆
So this is pretty awesome
所以这个是蛮厉害的
so be sure to wear gloves
所以一定要戴手套
The experiment it does is to put a magnet on this high-temperature conductor
它做的实验就是要把一个磁铁放在这个高温操导体
Hang it up, hang it up from that cup, hang it up
把它吊起来,从那杯子里把它吊起来,吊鱼
Hanging fish is a fun place, there is no line for hanging fish
吊鱼可是这个是好玩的地方,吊这个鱼没有线
That is, Jiang Taigong does not use a line to hang fish, and he also does not use a line to hang fish
就是姜太公吊鱼不用线,它这个也是吊鱼不用线
it has no wires but it won't soak
它没有线,但它不会泡
It can be sent to the high temperature conductor itself
它能夠送到高溫操導體本身
there is no rope to pull it up
沒有任何繩子把它拉起來
it can pull the material out of it
它可以把材料把它拉出來
from inside this cup of it
從它的這個杯子裡面
can go pull it out
可以去把它拉出來
so it has a magnet on it
所以它這個上面有一個磁鐵在上面
so it's now stuck to its
所以它現在黏在它的那個
not your family
不是你們人家
stick to this
黏到這個
take it take it
把它把它
then if you look carefully
那你如果仔細看的話
it should only be five to ten seconds
它應該只有五到十秒
yes you only have five to ten seconds
對,你只有五到十秒
The reason for my show here is that the light consumption can be rushed through.
我這邊秀的原因就是這個光耗可以衝過去
there is nothing in it
它中間是沒有東西的
it's grungy
它是格格的
Empty, it's just not long enough
空的 只是這個時間不夠久
It's about to pull, it's not enough, it's space
它就要拉了 不夠它是隔空
But you can see that it's not very stable when you pull it up.
但是你可以看這樣子拉起來不是太穩定
wait a minute i'll talk about it this
等一下我會講它這個
Why is it not too stable
為什麼不是太穩定的原因
because when it is held
因為它持放上去的時候
It was put on after the tide island has been changed.
是在已經變潮島以後放上去了
You can see that the two are actually separated
你看它這兩個是其實隔開的
it didn't touch
它沒有碰在一起
This itself if not frozen
這個本身如果沒有冷凍的話
it can't be picked up
它是拿不起來的
So this can levitate it
所以這個可以把它懸浮起來
This is another kind, the magnetic point is below
這個是另外一種 它這磁點是在下面
you can tell it's floating
你看得出來它是浮起來的
and quite stable
而且相當穩
The one just now was not so stable
剛才那個就不是那麼穩
this is very stable
這個是很穩的
wait there is a reason
等一下有個原因
Why is it that one or two are a bit different
它為什麼一個兩個是有點不太一樣
It's a magnet that's already on it
它這個是磁鐵本來就在上面
under this track
在這個軌道下面
So it can float
所以它這個可以浮起來的
This is floating
這個就馳浮了
This can last a long time
這個可以搞滿久的
This time it's completely stopped
這次到它這個完全停住
I keep looking
我一直你看
this is so enjoyable
這多過癮
Of course it's fun to be inside the gate
人在柵裡面當然很過癮
Not this one
這個不是
that was done
那是有人做
Somebody make a person this big stand on it and float
有人做一個這麼大的人站在上面浮起來
this
這個
good
好
Thanks
謝謝
thank you both
謝謝你們兩位
good
好
explained
就解釋了
The place where this explanation was just now
剛才這個解釋的地方
it's this thing
就是這個東西的
The characteristic is the magnetic field of our home
特点就是我们家的磁场
Of course, the magnetic fields of the two homes are actually different.
当然这两个家的磁场其实不太一样
It can be said that this is
可以说这个的话是
Originally, the magnetic field acts on this
本来磁场就作用在这个
Before becoming superconducting
在没有变超导以前
The magnetic field is already acting on the material
磁场就已经作用在这个材料上面
and then you cool it down
然后你再把它冷却下来
This one originally had no magnetic field.
这个呢是本来这个没有磁场的
That you cool it first and then add the magnetic field
那个你先把它冷却以后再加磁场
These two are actually not the same
这两个其实不太一样
It can be seen that this is not stable
可以看出来这个就不太稳定
It's very stable when you pull it up
拉起来就这个很稳定
very stable species
非常稳的这个种
Of course there is a very simple reason for this
这个当然是有很简单的道理
But the most important reason is that these are
但是最重要的原因是这些都是
These superconductors don't like this magnetic field too much
这些超导太不喜欢这个磁场
so what does he do
所以他做什么事情呢
Of course it's easy
当然很简单
drain it
把它排掉
If it's not good and you don't like it, let it out
既然不好不喜欢就把它排出去
is their greatest practice
是他们的最大的做法
Well, of course, the situation of this discharge is like this
那这个当然这个排出去的情况是这样的
Usually we think of common metals
通常我们都想得普通金属
We all learned about Faraday
我们都学过法拉地
cognitive law
認識定律
That is, if you take a metal
就是你如果拿一個金屬
with a magnetic field
跟一個磁場
when you put in
你放進的時候
The magnetic field causes a current in the metal
磁場就會造成金屬的電流
Current is usually
電流通常的
Sensing direction
感應方向
Just enough to cancel your magnetic field
剛好會抵消你的磁場
but ordinary metal
可是通常的金屬
not very strong
不會很強
because of what
因為什麼
because of current
因為有電流
there will be resistance
就會有電阻
at last there will be no more
最下就沒有了
The current is gone
電流就沒了
So other than this is not very strong
所以這個以外不是很強
but in dick too
但是在操導太
This current will not disappear
這個電流不會消失
So its current can be very strong
所以它這個電流可以很強
can stay for a long time
可以留很久
can generate a strong magnetic field
就可以產生很強的磁場
The two magnetic fields are of course opposite to each other.
這兩個磁場當然是互相相反
This is called shielding current
這個就叫屏蔽電流
that you now have
就是你現在有個
the experiment just now
剛才那個實驗
That is, a magnet is placed under it and above it.
就是它下面操導上面擺一個磁鐵
when it is placed like this
它這樣子擺上去的時候
This magnetic field goes from North Pole to South Pole
這個磁場從北極到南極
When going through this tutorial material
經過這個操導材料的時候
it is squeezed
它被擠壓
Look at this magnetic force line
大家看這個磁力線
It is logical that it should come down like this
它照道理它應該這樣子下來
But it's not it's squeezed out
可是它不是它被擠壓出去
How is it squeezed? Because the superconductivity here will generate a current
怎麼被擠壓呢?是因為這裡超導會產生一個電流
Just like ordinary metal, as I just said
就跟普通金屬一樣,就剛才講
If you add a permanent, it will generate current
你如果加一個持久,它會產生電流
The superconducting current will not disappear because it has no resistance
那超導電流不會消失,因為它沒有電阻
So it keeps flowing, and it produces the exact opposite
所以它一直在流,那它產生的剛好相反
It also generates a North Pole here
它也產生一個北極在這裡
The two north poles face each other, everyone will move if they know it
兩個北極相對,大家都曉得就會動
Yes, take two battery holders
對啊,拿兩個持電
Sometimes it's similar, sometimes it's different
有時候會相似,有時候會相次
Your North Pole is like the North Pole, and the North Pole is like the South Pole
你北極對北極就相似,北極對南極就相似
Then it happens to be North Pole to North Pole
那它這個剛好是北極對北極
This is the famous symbol
這個是著名的這個詞符
That is to say, this word has been known for a long time
就是說,這個詞符其實老早就知道
It doesn't have to be superconducting
它不一定用超導
But with superconductivity, this force becomes much larger
但用超導是這個力量變大很多
This is what I copied from the picture in their Shuangyuehai
這是我從他們的雙越海裡面的圖抄起來
I don't know how to draw this
我不曉得怎麼畫這個
They drew it very well, the magnetic lines look like this
他們畫得很好,那個磁力線這樣子
Look at this, bending like this actually creates force
你看這個,像這樣子的彎曲其實都會造成力
Because the lines of force don't like to bend like this
因為磁力線不喜歡這樣子彎
If you bend it like this, it will only compress tightly.
你把它這樣子彎曲會只能壓緊
So you can't fall, you can't hold down even with gravity
所以你這個掉不下去,有重力也壓不下去
Magnetic lines lift you up
磁力線把你抬起來
At that time, it was also said that there was an arctic market here.
當時當時也是說這裡有一個北極的市場
so lift him up
所以就把他抬升
that this is amazing
那這個是很神奇
because why doesn't he like
因為為什麼他不喜歡
that's what i just said
就是我剛講
because you're going to ruin his match
因為你要破壞他的配對
You have to make him not able to dance there harmoniously
你要讓他這個不能夠很和諧地在那邊跳舞
make him unhappy
讓他不高興
what will he do
那他都怎麼辦
he puts you out
他就把你排掉
don't let you eat sugar
不讓你吃糖進去
This is of course an interesting thing
這個當然是很有趣的事情
This is what nature does automatically
這個是自然界自動會做的事情
get you out
把你排出去
That way, the energy is relatively low.
那這樣子是能量比較降低
This is just floating
這個就是剛才浮起來而已
But this buoy is only repulsive
可是這個浮只有排斥力
This brain is not very stable
這個大腦不是很穩
So just now it can be seen
所以剛才可以看出來
then he is not very stable
那他就不是很穩
In fact, some of this stuff will slowly seep in.
那事實上有一些這個東西會慢慢的滲進去
seeps into its edge
滲到它邊緣裡
Then this just said that MineSyn
那這個剛才就是說那個MineSyn
That's what happened just now
就是剛才那個現象
In fact, there is another way
那事實上還有一個做法
If your magnetic field strength is too high
如果你這個磁場強度太高了
it has another way
它有另外一種辦法
it can't be discharged
它排不掉了
because you are too strong
因為你太強了
What should he do then?
那他怎麼辦呢?
well , he confines you to a small space
好,他就把你局限在小的空間
Think about how clever this nature is
你想,這個自然界有多聰明啊
Then I can't deal with you, you are too strong
那我對付不了你了,你太強了
What am I doing? I keep all your magnetic fields small
我幹嘛?我把你所有的磁場都局限在小的範圍
Just like the pillars, the same pillars you just jumped on
就跟柱子一樣,剛才跳的柱子一樣
then i'll be fine i'm old
那我就沒事了,我一樣個老啊
nothing to do with me
跟我沒什麼大的關係
what he can do
那他可以做的事
Someone figured this out
那這個事,有人解出來了
Then this thing is, let's talk about it later and get the road sign to talk about it
那這個事就是,等一下講就拿到路標講好
Well, this thing is very interesting. It's called a mixing station.
那這個事是很有趣的,叫混合台
That is, some lines of magnetic force are discharged to the outside, and some are mixed in.
就是有些磁力線被排到外面,有些混在裡面
The one in that row, this one is called
那排的這個,這個叫
Just now we called the Myzen effect
剛才我們那個叫做Myzen effect
It's weird that this guy didn't get the road sign
很奇怪,這個人沒拿到路標講
This, this has got the road sign to tell
這個,這個有拿到路標講
Arranged in a small space, this is called a mixing table
排在很小的空間,這個叫做混合台
Well, this is of course very important
那這個,這個當然是很重要
Then the mixing station mentioned just now is actually even more mysterious if you really look at it carefully.
那剛才講的這個混合台,其實真正仔細看,更奇玄奇了
That is, you still had this shielding current just now.
就是你剛才還是有這個屏蔽電流
I just said that you have shielding current when you hold the field.
剛才我講了你持場就有屏蔽電流
This pool line will go in
這個池線就會進去
Then we discovered the pool line
然後我們才發覺池線
It's actually a pool
其實是量池的
Each pool line has a certain pool moment
每一個池線都有一定的池矩
not casual
不是隨便的
we usually talk about pool
我們通常講池
Let's talk about 0.1 high humidity or Tesla
我們就講0.1個高濕或者是Tesla
0.001 is the speed per hour
0.001都是用時速
continuous
continuous
but here to tell you it's not
但是這裡告訴你它不是
In this quantum state
在這個量子態裡面
This thing itself is a quantum number
這個東西本身都是量子數
Each of these original rights represents a certain basic holding
每一個這原權代表一定的基本的持同量
Everyone is well arranged
每一個都排的好好的
Here it's actually neatly drawn
這裡它畫的其實很整齊
Each has six neighboring triangular lattices next to it
每一個旁邊有六個鄰居三角金格
This is Abbey Kossoff narrating
這個是Abbey Kossoff解說
It is what I talked about in 2003 with the Noble Watch
就是我講的2003年拿諾表講
Just because I solved it
就是因為解了
mainly a job
主要就是個工作
Let him speak with a watch
讓他拿諾表講
Is to lift this Ubricos of lattice
就是解除這個Ubricos of lattice
This proof is of course too much time to prove now
這個證明當然現在太多時間證明
this is right
這個是對的
you can go straight to it
你可以直接去看它
You sprinkle some iron powder on it
你把它撒一些鐵粉在上面
You can look directly at this magnetic flux
你可以直接看這個磁通量
how
怎樣
Of course each one has a vortice
那每一個當然是有個vortice
there is no superconducting team in it don't like to be in it
在這裡面是沒有超導隊不喜歡在裡面
superconducting team is right outside it
超導隊就在它外面
All the superconducting teams are out of it
所有的超導隊都在它外面
make a fuss
鬧著轉
It's like you've got lots of assistants and you're dancing
就跟你有很多助手你在跳舞一樣
You are making trouble with the assistant
你就是鬧著助手轉
then don't run inside
那你不要跑到裡面去
That's what they do electronically
那這個就是他們電子做的事情
Then this CobraPack is amazing
那這個CobraPack很神奇
he would do it himself
他自己會幹這種事
and not one or two
而且不是講一個兩個
That's what everyone does
那個是大家都做這個事情
That's what I just said
那剛才講這個東西
Why is it more stable?
為什麼比較穩呢
In fact, the magnetic flux is in this
其實這個磁通量在這個裡面
will also lock
也会锁住
it's somewhere
它有些地方
For example, some impurities
比如说有些杂质
it likes to be in the impurities
它就喜欢在杂质
We just said that impurities are not very good, right?
我们刚才讲杂质也不是很好 对不对
When there is this magnetism
那有这个磁的时候
This magnetic flux will be hired on the impurity
这个磁通量就会聘在杂质上
very strong
很强
So just say that
所以刚才讲那个
Just now this experiment here
刚才这边这个实验这个
this small
这个小
This experiment with this little train
这个小火车的这个实验
It's on top of this
它上面就是摆这个
because it is in the magnetic field
就是因为它在磁场里面
The magnet is already inside
那个磁本来就在里面
you cool it down
你把它冷却
All the magnetic flux goes inside.
这个磁通量都跑到里面去了
just stay in there
就在里面固定住
so locked
所以就锁住了
equal to lock
等于锁住
when you lift it up now
你现在把它提起来的时候
This magnetic flux has no place to run
这磁通量没地方跑
Everything inside is equivalent to being locked.
通通在里面就等于锁住了
So it's like an invisible rope
所以等于有个无形的绳子
the rope you can't see
你看不见的绳子
In fact, this material can be smashed
其实把这个材料可以砸掉
very stable
非常稳定
So it runs very stable
所以它跑的时候很稳定
it can't move
它没办法动
because so much
因为那么多
stay still
都要定住
it can't move
它没办法动
The one just now is because you didn't add it at the beginning
刚才那个是因为你一开始没加
no magnet here
这里没有磁
You later surpassed to have
你后来已经超到有
you want to add
你要想加进去
In fact it is added next to
其实它是加在旁边
very weak
很微弱的
beside
旁边
so it's not very stable
所以它不是很稳定
So I can't live if I smashed it like that just now
所以刚才那样砸起来不生活
there is a difference between the two
這兩個有差別
If it is placed in a magnetic field first and then cooled
如果是先放在磁場裡面再冷卻
The two results are not the same
跟後放這兩個結果是不太一樣
This result is to tell you
這個結果就是告訴你
This is a company with a very stable employment
這個是有一個所屍內非常穩定的雇用
so what can this be used for
所以這個可以拿來做什麼
can be used as an application
就可以拿來做應用
Now we understand this thing
現在我們理解了這個東西
we also know why
我們也知道它為什麼
Because the Cooper team wants everyone to be harmonious
因為這個Cooper隊這個要大家要和諧
if you mess up
你如果亂七八糟
some of the others it's not good
有些別的當中它都不好
But it has a way to solve this problem
但它有想辦法來解決這個問題
it can solve this problem
它可以解決這個問題
Make a Perfect Solution
做一個Perfect的Solution
All of this I just talked about is consciousness
所有這些我剛講的都是意識
Of course quantum mechanics can help you figure it out
當然量子力學可以幫你算出來
Everything I said can be calculated exactly
每一樣我講的東西都可以Exactly算出來
This is an incredible result of the BCS theory
這個是BCS理論的一個不得了的成果
It is not possible to do this quantitatively
不是可以量化做這個事情
alright
好了
But there is another not-so-good place in BCS theory
但從BCS理論上又有一個不太好的地方
Its temperature probably won't exceed 40 degrees
它的溫度大概不會超過40度
Because someone has done the math on how hard it is for me to increase the temperature
因為有人算過這個問題,就是說我要想把溫度增加有多困難
Because it must have a strong electron ion
因為它一定要有很強的電子離子
We just talked about the role of biomass, right?
我們剛才講了生質的作用,對不對?
Electrons and biomass must have an attractive force to dig a hole for it to enter
電子跟生質要有一個吸引力把它挖一個洞,它進去
It must be very strong, the stronger it is, the deeper the hole will be dug, and the faster it will fall, right, the better
要有很強,越強當然挖得洞越深,掉得越快對不對,越好
But you also need a high electron density, that is, a lot of electrons
但是你還需要有高電子太密度,就是電子要滿多的
At a certain energy, there must be many electrons in a place close to the low energy
某一個能量,在一個接近低能量的地方要有很多電子
But there is no superconductivity without electrons
但是如果沒電子的話也沒有超導
So it's impossible for an insulator to superconduct, right?
所以絕緣體是不可能超導對不對
But if you want to put electrons in it, it needs to be superconducting, the more the better
但是你要有辦法把電子放進去它就要超導,那越多越好
Then these two must be very large, but when these two are very large, there are actually other problems
那這兩個都要很大,可是這兩個很大的時候其實也有別的問題
When this is too strong, like this strong, if this thing is getting stronger
當這個太強的時候,像這麼強,如果這個東西越來越強
This electron can't escape anymore
這個電子又跑不出來了
Then we just said that it will continue to dance.
那我們剛才講它要繼續跳舞啊
This is not jumping all the time, jumping from here to that two people have to switch
這不是一直跳,從這裡頭跳到那兩個人就要交換
run around, then you may...
到處跑,那你才可能...
Synchronize Harmony
Synchronize 和諧
it jumps now if you don't give it
它現在如果你不給它跳
Each is fixed in a certain area
每個都固定在某一個區域
That's an insulator
那就絕緣體了
You cushion it, even if you add cushions, it can’t jump out
你墊子 你加墊它也跳不出來
it can't conduct
它沒有辦法傳導
that's over, that's over
那就完了 那又不行了
So it has a limitation
所以它這裡面就有一個限制
That is to say, if you are too strong
就是說你如果太強了
I can't help it either
我也沒辦法
Too weak and I don't have superconductivity
太弱了 我又沒超導
Then I have to be stronger to resist my rejection point
那我要強一點要抵抗我的排斥點
I just said that there is a cool person effect
我剛剛講有酷人作用力
So there is a lot of balance in it
所以這裡面是很多balance
have a balance
要有一個平衡
that sometimes more
那有時候多
That's why we want the temperature to be higher, higher and higher
那可是我們想要溫度更高更高更高
Then how do you get this out
那你這個就怎麼樣弄出來
So this question was originally
所以這個問題就當初
Someone suggested that it is impossible to exceed 40 degrees
就有人提出來說不可能超過40度
This question is of course very frustrating
這個問題當然是很令人沮喪
Because we just showed 1980
因為我們剛才秀了到1980年
Of course people who do experiments, people who do physics
當然要做實驗的人 做物理的人
never respond
從來不會相應
What is the limit
什麼有limit
we still have to try
大家還是要試
keep trying
繼續試
Then someone tried it
那就有人做這個試了
Then of course do this test
那這個做這個試當然就
That's what you see all the way here until 1986
就是你看一直到這裡 一直到1986年
A total of 74 years later
一共74年以後
These two people won the Nobel Prize
這兩個人拿諾貝爾獎
This was in 1913 and he made it in 1911
這是1913年 他1911年做出來的
He was made in 1986
他是1986年做出來的
Received the Nobel Prize in 1987
1987年就拿諾貝爾獎
The Battle of Mirror
The Battle of Mirror
because why
因為為什麼呢
Because Wu Maokun and Zhu Jinwu helped them dance
因為是吳茂坤和朱金武幫他們蹦
jump from here to here
從這裡就跳到這裡了
this is liquid egg
這是液態蛋
So I can now do this experiment and show you guys here
所以我現在可以做這個實驗在這裡秀你們
because they made the material
就是因為他們做了這個材料
it would be hard if i was here
如果我在這裡的話 我就很難了
I'm going to do liquid harm
我要去搞液態害
Liquid Hazard is very expensive now
液態害現在很貴
One liter costs five or six hundred Taiwan dollars
一公升要五六百台幣
and very troublesome
而且很麻煩
evaporated in one go
一下就蒸發掉了
very expensive
貴得很
But liquid eggs are cheap
可是液態蛋很便宜
about as cheap as beer
大概跟啤酒一樣便宜
So it's very convenient to follow this
所以就跟這個就很方便了
then i can show you guys here
那我可以在這裡秀你們
as soon as they make it
他們一做出來
This is 90 degrees
這個90幾度
Afterwards, everyone followed suit and made similar materials.
那後來馬上大家跟著做類似的材料
all these are
這些都是
The same series has been here
同一系列就一直到这里
Of course here we have stopped for many years now
当然在这里我们现在停了很多年了
here comes the problem
问题就来了
where to find
去哪里找
Four temperature operation
四温操刀
But of course this is a very big jump
可是这个当然是一个非常大的跳脚
jump from here to here
从这里跳到这里
the whole situation has changed
整个情况都变了
because it immediately has a large impact on the application
因为它马上对应用来讲有很大的
This is of course our year
这个当然我们那年
I have to attend this March Meeting
我有去参加这个March Meeting
Everyone is like the wind
大家像发风一样
so old man
那么老的人
You see, they are all great physicists.
你看都是大物理学家
this is night
这个是晚上
Everyone rush to this special
大家赶去参加这个特别的
Because this is their paper coming out in January
因为这个是他们的paper是一月出来
This meeting will be held in March
三月要开这个会
This is the largest open-ended physics meeting of the American Physical Society
这是美国物理学会最大的零开物理会议
There were two to three thousand people at that meeting
那个会议那次两三千人
Of course it's tens of thousands now
现在当然都上万了
There are only two or three thousand people for this mission
这个任务只有两三千人
But the waterlines of a few are different
但是几的水线不同
That hall is full of people
那个厅里面全部都是人
don't sleep at night
晚上都不睡觉
stop eating
不吃饭了
everyone ran to listen
大家跑去要听
everyone wants
每个人都要
everyone has a speech
每个人都有讲话
few minutes if you have new results
几分钟 如果你有新的结果
because they came out
因为他们才出来
Everyone hurry back and do it
大家就赶快回去做
Actually I remember that time
其实我记得那时候
I'm doing theory
我是做理论
Our colleagues
我们的同事
We at Virginia Tech
我们在Virginia Tech
Our colleagues are also burning this material
我们的同事也有在烧这个材料
everyone is doing
大家都在做
Let him measure this and that
让他去量这个 量那个
say everyone has to go
说每个都要去
Can't talk for five minutes
上不去讲五分钟
say what we did
说我们做了什么
what did we do
我们做了什么
what did you measure
量了什么
There are a lot of people crowded in Allah
阿拉里面挤的非常多人
You have to listen to this high tide early
都要听这个高温潮早
this is a
这个是一个
This is Wuastau
这个叫Wuastau
Do you think of this story?
大家想的这个故事吗
Wuastau this is the concert
Wuastau这是这个音乐会
is an american concert
是美国的音乐会
This is Wuastau in physics
这个就是在物理界的Wuastau
This situation is hard to find now
这种情况现在是很难找的
unless you find now
除非你现在找到
Lume Time Media Subbattlete
Lume Time Media Subbattlete
You can Battle
你可以Battle
Because it's better than this
因为比这个还厉害
Everyone will be squeezed out
这个全部人都要挤挤去
what about this
这个呢
Of course this picture is my favorite
当然这个图我是最喜欢的
This is Time Magazine
这是Time Magazine的
Picture from May 11th
5月11号的图
Look, wow, I jumped up excitedly
你看 哇 兴奋的跳起来
This temperature keeps going up
这个温度一直上去
Say Heating Up
说Heating Up
they are good at writing these
他们很会写这些
very nice cover
非常好的一个封面
This is an important breakthrough for them
這個是他們一個重要的突破
Of course there are many applications
當然有很多應用的出來
Let's talk about the various possible applications
大家就講說各種可能的應用
This is Mueller
這是Mueller
Flocks
Bandos
The Mueller two
這個Mueller兩個
Take the Noble watch to say happy
拿諾表講高興
This is what I just said
這個剛才我講的就是
ran here suddenly
忽然之間跑到這裡
in fact a few years ago
事實上幾年以前
In 2008 there was another group
2008年的時候有另外一組
temperature high temperature superconducting industry out
溫度高溫超導業出來
This group has the highest temperature
這組的溫度最高
now it's 55 degrees
現在到55度
I'm not just waiting for me to talk
本來還不只等下我在講
still higher
還有更高
related to this group
跟這組有關的
it's iron
這是鐵的
This is copper
這邊是銅
here is iron
這裡是鐵
The most important element here is copper
最重要的元素這裡是銅
The most important element is iron
最重要的元素是鐵
This is also strange
這個也是奇怪
Because iron is magnetic
因為鐵是有磁性
how can this be superconducting
這怎麼會超導
Here are all materials that are not magnetic
這裡都是不是磁性的材料
all here
所有的這裡的
you can watch
你可以看
Neither are magnetic materials
都不是磁性材料
At that time, it was not possible to use magnetism for angles.
那時候角度用磁性是不行的
it's here
在這裡
All of a sudden a complete change
忽然之間全面改觀
This is also magnetic
這個也有磁性的
so the whole
所以整個
the whole is
整個都是
After super-temperature operation, I found a lot of confusion
超温操導出來就發覺有很多的困惑
Then let me talk about its application first.
那我先講它的應用好了
I may be a little slow
我可能有點慢了
The application I'm going to talk about will be over soon
我要講的應用很快就過去
Everyone may laugh about the energy crisis
大家可能都笑得到能源危機什麼
If you can find energy storage materials
你如果能找到能源儲存材料
Renewable Energy and Savings
再生能源跟節省
Don't turn electricity into heat
費電就不要把電都變成熱
it will be much better, right?
就會好很多對不對
We're all turning electricity into heat now
我們現在都把電變成熱了
But the problem is that you need
但是這個問題就是你需要
If there is a conductor
如果有操導體
That manipulator can now do a lot of things with magnets
那操導現在可以做的東西很多磁鐵
I just said that because it doesn't
那剛才我講因為它沒有
It does not consume this current
它這個電流沒有消耗
Therefore, a large current can be passed
所以可以通很大的電流
Why couldn't magnets be made before?
那以前磁鐵為什麼不能做
What can't be done with this current wire
用這個電流線來做不能做
because you're going to be very hot
因為你會變熱很熱
So you burn out this one
所以你這個一下就燒壞
So transformer
那所以transformer
almost often the small ones will break
差點常常小的會壞掉
Transformers often say
就會變壓器常常說
Whoa, the transformer exploded.
哇 變壓器爆炸壞掉
it's too hot and there's trouble
太熱了就會有個麻煩
That wire is thick
那電線濃了
then you start leaking
那你就開始漏電走
trouble
麻煩
So if you don't have a resistor
那所以你如果沒有電阻
Of course you can put a lot of current
當然可以放很大的電流
you put the car up
你把車子列起來
You can make a cable to pull electricity from the power plant
你做Cable把電從電廠拉出來都可以
Then you can do this MRI
然後你可以做這個MRI
This is quantum interference
這個是量子乾涉
In fact, you can also do MRI, what is it called?
其實也可以做MRI叫什麼
NMR
核磁共振儀
It can also be used as a super disturbance green wave machine
還可以做超擾綠波機
This is an existing product
這個是已經有產品的
Super disturbance green wave machine and so on
超擾綠波機等等的
I won't talk much
我就不多講
The main thing is of course
主要的當然是
like Japan made this stone ax train
像日本做了這個石斧列車
too much to eat
超到吃點
Its benefit is of course energy saving
它的好處當然是節能
Low noise and high speed can reach 550
低噪音高速可以到550
This is twice the speed of our high-speed rail
這個是我們的高鐵的一倍的速度
can reach this speed
可以到這樣子的速度
This is the establishment of superconducting Cable in the United States
這是在美國在建立超導的Cable電纜
for electricity
要出電用
They're the latest in Albany, the richest man in New York
他們在最新的是在紐約的首富Albany
make this cable
做這個電纜
this is very complicated
這個是很複雜
high temperature superconductor
這裡面有高溫超導
Then pick up this Nitrogen
那有接這個Nitrogen
It's the liquid nitrogen we just mentioned.
就是剛才講的液態氮
in it
在這裡面
Then there are copper wires outside
然後外面還接銅線
I'm afraid that if something goes wrong
怕萬一出問題
Immediately this current is so big
馬上這個電流那麼大
it's a big deal
就不得了的事
so there must be another emergency rescue
所以要有另外的緊急的救援
This is also done with the Koreans
這個也是跟韓國人在做
This is the continental superconducting system
這個是大陸超導系統
The mainland is also doing
大陸也在做
Started to make this cable system in 2012
2012年開始做這個電纜系統
business
事業
make this superconducting
做這個超導
OK
OK
The whole world is progressing
這個全世界都在進展
Japan also bought an American company
日本也買了一家美國的公司
Super Power
Super Power
bought it
把它買去了
and then they
然後他們就
This is about Power density
這個是說Power density
you can get there
就可以到
It can pull up to 816 meters
它可以拉到816米
Such a long cable
這麼長的Cable
572 amps already
已經有572個安培的電流
that's big
那是很大的
Awesome
很厲害了
has become more and more
已經越來越
This is strong, this line is of course going up
這個強了,這個線當然是往上走
Of course, the stronger the better, you can pull electricity for several kilometers
當然越強越好,你可以拉幾公里的電來
And if there are more than 500 arrangements, of course it is a very good transmission system
然後如果都有五百多安排,當然是非常好的這個傳電系統
So here they have, and there are Korean companies that are also doing this
所以這裡他們有,那有這個是韓國的公司也在做這個事情
So the major countries are doing this
所以這個主要的國家都在做這個
The other one is to do non-human energy storage
那另外一個就是做非人儲能
Inhumans have actually used it to store energy for a long time
非人是其實老早就用了來儲能
But that object is because you have kinetic energy, because the energy of rotation
但是那個的物體就是因為你有動能,因為轉動的能量
You let that thing if there is no friction a thing keeps turning
你讓那個東西如果沒有摩擦的一個東西一直在轉
You can treat it as if you turn it faster and faster to transfer energy into it
你就可以把它當作,你把它越轉越快就把能量傳進去
When you want to take it out, let it work with a certain
等你要拿出來的時候,就讓它去跟某一個作用
Let it think slowly, let it transfer energy to another
讓它慢慢慢慢想,讓它把能量傳遞給另外一個
As for this non-human being, it is of course better to use the drill now, because there is no friction
那這個非人,那現在用操導當然是更好,因為沒有friction
So it can do a good job, the first one published by Superpower America
所以它可以做得很好,那這個Superpower美國的這個發表的第一個這個
Storage now saves energy
現在就Storage存能量的
stored energy is a large
存能量是一個很大的
Staying true to energy is important
依守在能源是很重要的事情
So this is a very important technique
所以這個是非常重要的一個技術
Of course you can do what you just said
當然可以做來剛才講的
NMR etc.
核磁共振等等的
you need big magnets
你需要很大的磁鐵
Now of course in the collider of the High Energy Experiment
現在當然在高能實驗的對撞機
They all use super old magnets.
都用的就是超老磁鐵
because it is relatively small
就是因為它面積比較小
but smaller
但是體積比較小
But its amount and duration are much larger
但它的量時長是大很多
because it has no discretion
因為它沒有discretion
so much better
所以又好很多
of course you have to cool it
當然你要給它酷
you need a cooling system
你要有冷卻系統
OK but the confusion of high temperature superconductors
OK 但高溫超導體的困惑
Let's talk about its confusion now
我們現在來講它的困惑
this all sounds good
這個聽起來都很好
But we found a lot of strange things
可是我們發覺有很多事情很奇怪
This is a picture we made ourselves
這個是我們自己弄的一張圖
I asked my postdoc to go and look up those things
我請我的博士後弄了去查那些東西
what does this picture mean
這個是這個圖的意思是什麼
This is its superconducting transition temperature
這個是它的超導轉變溫度
with it at room temperature right now
跟它的在室溫的時候就現在
If you measure its resistivity
你如果去量它的電阻率
you take log
你take log
Because the number is far from
因為這個數字差很遠
many times
很多倍
So with this scheme, the difference is 10 to the power of one
所以用這個方案就差10的一次方
This is 10 to the power of -1
這個是10的-1次方
This 10 to the power of -2
這個10的-2次方
Resistivity
電阻率
Then you can see these new
那就可以看見新的這些
superconducting iron
超導鐵 鐵的同的
all in this paragraph
都是在這一段
are high resistivity
都是電阻率很高的
But they usually also have a higher TC
但它們通常TC也比較高
But this one is old like quicksilver
但這一點就是舊的像水銀
The 23 degrees mentioned just now are all here
這個剛才講23度都在這裡
TC is lower here
這裡的TC比較低
But its resistivity is very low at room temperature
但是它的電阻率在室溫的時候都很低
means it's a good metal
就表示它是很好的金屬
You measure it at room temperature and say these are good metals
在室溫的時候你去量說這些都是好金屬
these are bad metal
這些都是壞金屬
Later found another MGB2
後來又找到了一個MGB2
See it is the same as the old one
看到它也是跟舊的一樣
Its resistivity is also very low
它的電阻率也是很低
just at room temperature
就是在室溫裡面
These are good conductors
這些都很好的導鐵
can be used for normal
可以拿來做平常
the same wire or something
同的導線什麼等等
this is very good
這是很好的
But this is all bad
但是這個都是不好
Here's a weirder one
這裡有一個更奇怪的
very complicated
很複雜的
This is called organic
這是一個叫做organic
organic superconductor
就是有機超導體
Stranger and Larger Molecules
更奇怪的很大的分子
very complicated
很複雜的
This is also very resistive
這個也是電阻率很高
But the temperature is also around 20 degrees
但是溫度也到20度左右
So it's kind of weird
所以這有著很奇怪的現象
Usually we think
通常我們都是認為
More conductive metals should be better at superconducting
越導電的金屬應該越好超導
that was the old idea
那是以前的想法
BCS also predicts like this
BCS也是這樣子預測
But now I find that this kind of new ones are not
可是現在發覺這一類的新的都不是
It's a bad resistor
是電阻不好了
very bad
很差了
On the contrary, superconducting temperature is very high
反而是超導溫度很高
this is strange
這個是奇怪
The other is that these are bilingual systems
另外一個就是這些都是二文系統
is copper
就是銅
You see copper is a plane
你看銅是一個平面
another plane
另外一個平面
another circle
另外一個圓
The main superconductivity is in the copper plane
主要的超導都在銅平面
The main superconductivity is in the iron plane
這個主要超導都在鐵的平面
most
大部分
They all look like two-dimensional systems when their electrons move
它們的電子運動的時候看起來都像是二維系統
It's not three-dimensional, so it's very different from before
不是三維,所以跟以前又很不一樣
some features of this
這啥的一些特性
Something else weird is that these superconducting states
另外一些奇怪的地方是這些超導的態
If you dope you can make it superconducting or not superconducting
如果你摻雜的時候你可以把它變成超導不超導
But it's all similar to this magnetic
但它都跟這個磁性很像
This phase diagram is if I put different numbers to replace a certain atom
這個相圖就是如果我放不同的數目的來代替某一個原子
If silk is used instead of blue, if it is replaced by a little
像絲來代替藍的話,代替一點的話
The more I replace, the more I become superconducting
代替越多我就變超導
Instead of a little I am antiferromagnetic
代替一點點我是反鐵磁
is magnetic
就是磁性
Upper wisdom and lower wisdom are ranked
上智學跟下智學是排的
one up next next up
一個上一個下一個上一下
It is equal to the blue, red, blue and red gold grids arranged well
等於是藍紅藍紅的金格排的好好的
a square square
一個正方金格
Next to your blue is red
你隔壁藍的旁邊都是紅色的
blue next to red
紅的旁邊就是藍色的
This is a well-arranged antiferromagnetic
這樣子排的好好的反鐵磁
But if you put a little more in it, it becomes superconducting
但是你如果再多放一點來它就變超導了
But it's so close
可是它這個就靠得很近
Another point is that the product superconductivity of iron is the same
還有一點這個鐵的積超導也是同樣的
they have many similarities
它们有很多类似的地方
But this is a phenomenon that the old superconductors did not have before.
可是这个是以前旧的超导体没有的现象
The farther away they are from persistence the better
它们离持性越远越好
So there is no persistent material
所以都没有持性的材料
But this persistence is quite high
可是这个持性都蛮高的
The sustaining temperature is actually quite high, 300 degrees here
这持性温度其实还蛮高 300度这里
so strong persistence
所以很强的持性
But instead a very high superconducting temperature
但是反而很高的超导温度
this is very strange
这是很奇怪的
This is the Waterfall team I was talking about
这是刚才我讲的那个瀑布队
don't like holding sex
不喜欢持性
What did you do, persistent
你怎么搞的 有持性的
The organic superconductivity just mentioned
这个刚才讲的有机超导
also near here
也是在这个附近
All the shopkeepers around here have poor sight temperatures
所有在这附近的店主带视温都很差
don't even think about it
也不悉想
because it has persistence in it
因为它有持性在里面
bumping, bumping, bumping
搞来搞去撞来撞去的
so it doesn't like
所以它也不喜欢
But its superconducting temperature is very high
但是它商务号超导温度很高
Of course everyone thinks about it
当然大家要想了
how do i solve this problem
我怎么来解决这问题
How can I help form a CooporPair
我怎么来帮忙形成CooporPair
Coopor team
Coopor队
possible communication we have already talked about reproduction
可能的交际我们已经讲了生殖
Of course everyone wants to do theory
当然大家想做理论
Of course you can sit at home and think a lot
当然可以坐在家里想很多很多了
We also did this plasma
我们也做过这个等离子
Plasma
Plasma
You don't understand, it means you have a lot of batteries
大家聽不懂就是說你有很多電池
Because positively charged ions are on the grid
因為有正電的離子在金格上
Then you have electrons that can run around and it can go the right way
那你有電子可以跑來跑去 它可以正道
Collective Righteous Way It is not just one or two electricity, many electric righteousness
集體正道 它不是一兩個電的 很多電正道
Of course, if there is the right way, there will be more batteries here.
當然有正道的話 就會有一下這邊多電池
There is less battery over there, less battery looks like righteousness
那邊少電池 少的電池就看起來像正氣
Positive and multi-battery, this kind of positive way can also cause two batteries
正多電池 這樣子的正道也可以造成兩個電池的
Of course, this has never been found. This is a theory that is often said.
當然這個從來沒被找到過 這個是理論常常有講
And then there's another one that we notice because electrons also have a magnetic moment
然後還有一個我們注意到就是因為電子它也有磁矩
We just mentioned that there is a magnetic whirl, so we have the body just mentioned
剛才講有磁旋 那我們一隻剛才講的這個身子
Everything uses the force of cool people because it uses electric charges
什麼都是用的是酷人作用力 因為用電荷的
We did not talk about the influence of the magnetic moment, if there is a magnetic moment
我們沒有講磁矩的影響 它如果有磁矩
It can also work by itself, just the magnetic force of the magnetic wire is working
它本身也可以作用 就磁線磁力在作用
It doesn't have to rely on the effect of charge, so there are other possibilities.
那不一定是要靠電荷作用 那這個就有別的可能性了
Then this is what I just said about high temperature exceeding the body. We just talked about it.
那這個是我剛講高溫超到體 我們剛才講
This is the super-body mentioned by Naobiao.
這就是拿諾表講的那個超到體 它把來
Replaced a little bit with back heel silk
用背跟絲取代了一點點
If not it's as simple as
如果沒有的話它很簡單
very nice a jingle
非常好的一個金格
well arranged
排得好好的
The red inside is copper
裡面都是這個紅的就是銅
next to copper is oxygen
銅旁邊就是氧
Below the middle is a large pile of this blue or stone
下面中間的是一大堆這個藍的或石
Blue if you want Ginger not
如果你要金格沒有的話就是藍
That's copper oxide again
那又是銅氧
Copper Oxygen Plane Again
又是銅氧的平面
if so
如果這樣子的話
I drew all the copper planes
我把所有銅的平面畫出來
it is each with a word string
它就是每一個都有一個字弦
This is the anti-iron pool I just mentioned
這個就是我剛才講的反鐵池
one up one down one up one down
一上一下一上一下
Well lined up
排得金格排得好好的
This is its anti-iron pool
這個就是它的反鐵池
But in fact we remember
但是事實上我們又記得
We are in a quantum world
我們在量子的世界
Quantum doesn't like things that don't move
量子不喜歡不動的
Didn't I say it just now?
剛才我不是講了
it doesn't like you not moving
它不喜歡你不動
High energy due to motionless
因為不動就能量高
This sea cucumber treasure is not sure how far away
這個海參寶不確定很遠的
so what does it do
所以它要幹嘛呢
It still needs to exchange the two
它這兩個還是要交換
You can imagine everyone doing row after row
你可以想像大家做了一排一排
Well done Blue Red Blue Red Ginger
藍紅藍紅金格做得好好的
Swap the blue one with the red one
一下子藍的跟紅的交換一下
exchange over there again
一下子那邊又交換一下
swap it and swap it back
交換一下它又交換回來
just keep swapping
就這樣一直交換交換來
it swaps to go , but an average of one-fifth swaps again
它交換去,但是平均五分之一再交換
If you take a photo at any time, about one-fifth of it is an exchange
你如果隨時照一張相,大概五分之一是交換
But most of them are in the right place
不過大部分都是在對的位置
This is probably the state when it is half full.
這個大概就是在半填滿的時候的狀態
This is because of quantum effects, making it exchange
這個是因為量子效應,讓它要交換
This exchange is like what you just said, think about it, it's like red
這個交換你剛才講的那樣,你想想這是紅的那樣
but it can't run very far
但是它跑不了太遠
because it's coming back soon
因為它一下子就要回來
It's in the wrong place, the energy is a little higher
它在錯的位置,這個能量比較高一點
so it likes to come back, after a while it jumps back
所以它喜歡回來,它過一下它又跳回來
But it's not okay to stay still, so it jumps around
但它不動是不行的,所以它跳來跳去
This is a very simple quantum action
這個是很簡單的量子作用
Now if we use back or silk instead
現在如果我們用背或絲來代替的時候
There were originally three blue planes, but two on the back
這藍本來三架,背是兩架
So it has one less electron
所以它的電子少了一個電子
So there are fewer electrons in it.
所以這裡面就少放了電子進去
The same surface suddenly lost an electron
同樣面忽然之間少了一個電子
It means that there is a hole, that is, the electron is removed.
就是有空洞,就是把這個電子拿掉了
it has an extra hole
它多了一個空洞
that's even better
那下就更好了
Because he just said he doesn't like to stop there
因為剛才講他不喜歡停在那裡
He just jumps right into the hole now
他現在就直接跳到空洞就好了
He has one more, the emperor can jump to the vacant seat
他多了一個 天子可跳到空位
So as soon as you have a void
所以你一有空洞以後
He started to play a little more role
他開始又多了一些作用
In addition to electron up-spin down-spin exchange
除了電子跟上至旋下至旋交換以外
he can jump with holes
他可以跟空洞跳
he keeps jumping
他一直跳
This jump is great
這個跳就很厲害了
Because of jumping, this arrangement is gone.
因為跳跳這個排列就不見了
As you can imagine, there are a lot of vacancies now
大家可以想像現在大家很多空位
If you are a blue building and the next door is red
如果你是藍樓 隔壁是紅的話
You are now asking you to change chairs
你現在叫你換椅子
It won't be a mess after a while
過一下就不排得很亂了
All of a sudden, the neatly arranged golden grids disappeared.
一下子原來排得整齊的金格就不見了
gone soon
很快就不見了
Of course it was broken up with this
當然跟這個就被打散了
He can move around again
他又到處可以移動了
Now the team can
現在這個隊就可以
not only in the original place
不只在原來地方
It turns out that you are all near
原來就是說你都是在臨近的
I can run far now
我現在可以跑很遠了
this team can run
這個隊就可以跑
This dry foil team starts again
這個枯箔隊又開始
like the one i just said
像我剛才講的那個
The situation where the dance was drawn
畫的那個跳舞的情況
he can run far
他可以跑很遠了
because now there are
因為現在有
If there is a hole, you can't run far without a hole, and if there is a hole, it's easy to run
有空洞了,没有空洞就跑不远,有空洞很容易跑了
This spaced one, this adjacent one, this one because of fanning
这个间隔的,这个邻近的,这个因为打扇的
So there isn't such a strong force to keep him in the same position
所以也没有这么强的力把他限制在他同一个位置
so he can run around
所以他可以到处来跑
Then dance with the Cooper team that we were talking about
那又跟我们原来讲的话的库博队那个跳舞
Come to think of it, it's actually very close
大家想想其实就很相近了
It doesn't make a difference because he's doing the same thing
没有什么差别,因为他也是在做同样的事情
One up, one down, one up and one down exchange over there
一个up,一个down,一个上一个下在那边交换
he is going to run
他就要跑去
That, that, that, when he said it like this, it would be resolved, it was the reason for the guidance
那这个,那这个,当他这样子讲就解决了就是操导的原因
Of course it's not that simple, because if you take a closer look
那当然没那么简单了,因为如果再仔细看看
He still has a lot to crawl, but I don't talk about so much confusion today
他还有很多爬走,但我今天不讲那么多的困惑
He has a lot of confusion, if you look carefully at any time, you will be confused
他的困惑非常多,随时看着仔细就有困惑
There is a very important experiment, which is the reason for the development of Naimi Technology
有一个很重要的实验,这是耐米科技发展的原因
I just invented this, this, that is a picture number I copied from someone else’s online inspection
就是发明了这个,这个,那是我从人家的那个摆在网验上抄下来的一个图号
This is called Scanning internally my...
就是这个叫做Scanning internally my...
scanning through sleep microscope
掃描穿睡顯微鏡
it has a very real extension
它有一個很真的增間
This is your original sample
這個是原來你的樣品
If you add a little bit of voltage to the current
如果加一點點電壓的電流
There are electrons that wear and sleep from here
就有電子從這裡穿睡
what can this do
這個可以來個什麼
can measure its height
可以量它的高低
each of which can be measured
可以量它的每一個哪一種
In particular, different electron densities are different
特別的不同的電子的密度不一樣
it can measure anything
它什麼都可以量
This is called STM
這個叫做STM
叫Scanning internally micro
叫Scanning internally micro
This is the work that won the Nobel Prize
這個是拿諾貝爾獎的工作
The whole nanotechnology starts here
整個奈米科技就從這裡開始了
Then if you read what I just said
那如果你去看這個剛才講的
High temperature superconducting samples
高溫超導的樣品
You see what it measures
你看它量得出來的結果
under the same voltage
在同一個電壓之下
This current is very uneven
這個電流非常不均勻
If you look closely, it is very uneven
你仔細看是非常不均勻
It's a bit like we're uneven here
這有點像我們這裡很不均勻
very messy
做得非常的亂
the one i was talking about
跟我剛才講的那個
Ordinary superconductors are different
平常超導體不一樣
Normal superconductors are perfect
平常超導體很完美
This is superconducting too cool
這個是超導太涼的
it's very uneven
它非常不均勻
Then carefully put this into these ten nanometers
那仔細再把這個放到這十個奈米
you make it bigger
你再把它放大
This is only four nanometers
這個是整個才四個奈米
Zoom in again
再放大
it looks at every atom
它看每一個原子
every copper atom
每一個銅原子
between two atoms
兩原子中間的
you are uneven
你也是不均勻的
this is incredible this measurement
這個是不得了的這個測量
we have a colleague now
我們現在有個同事
There are ways to measure more like this
有辦法多這樣子的測量
This makes its measurement
這個讓它的測量
measure out
量出來發掘
These are uneven
這些都不均勻的
Electrons are not uniform in this
電子在這裡面不均勻
This is like the dance I just mentioned
這個就像剛才我講的這個跳舞
there's more in dancing
那在跳舞裡面還有更多
more complicated
更複雜化
here's this jump time
在這裡的這個跳的時候
There is a group of people walking to the left
有一群人是往左邊走
There is a group of that Couple going to the right
有一群那個Couple隊往右邊走
So I will think a lot here
所以在這裡一下子會讓多想
less here
那這邊就變少
Just started everyone has updated shots
就開始大家有更新的拍的
Not only did it jump like this
不但是原來這樣子跳
It also has a certain mutual motion with each other
它還有彼此之間有一定的互相的運動
that's what you can imagine
那就是你可以想像
Some earth dances are so complicated
有些土逢舞就那麼複雜
Jumping is so complicated
跳起來就是有這麼複雜
This electron does complicated things
這個電子就做複雜的事情
it's still uneven
它還是不均勻
It's in Cao Daotai, so this is very novel
就是在曹岛太,那这个就很新奇
This is the old one from the past, it is the traditional Caodao, and it is completely non-existent
这个是以前的舊的,就是传统曹岛的,是完全没有的事情
Impossible things are here
不可能的事情,那这里都有了
It started to have various variations again
它又开始有各种不同的变化
This is what I just mentioned above
就是这个有刚刚回到上面讲的
When the force is very strong, the force here is of course very strong
在很强作用力的时候,这里的作用力当然是很强很强
The force of Kuren is very strong, this is a very strange thing
库人作用力非常强,这是很奇怪的事情
The strong Kuren force has a very high Caodao temperature
很强的库人作用力反而有很高的曹岛温度
That's the complete opposite, completely different from what we usually imagine
那是完全相反,跟我们平常想象是完全不一样
So in the bcs theory here is a big problem
所以在bcs理论在这里就碰到很大的问题
Now everyone believes that probably the bcs theory cannot explain this phenomenon
现在大家都相信,大概bcs理论是不能解释这个现象的
The main reason is that there is complexity
那主要的原因就是这里有复杂性
Far beyond this simplest theory
远超过了这个最简单的理论
So this is why we have been studying this for so many years
所以这个也是我们为什么做那么多年在研究这个
Now we understand that the electricity and number of this are different here
现在我们了解这个的电和数目在这里都不一样
everything is different
每一点都不一样
We haven’t measured this until the experiment. We can tell him that it’s different.
到實驗還沒量出來這個 我們可以跟他講是不一樣的
Now let's finally talk about higher superconducting temperatures.
那現在最後我們來講一下 更高超導溫度好了
There are several possibilities, one is to find new materials
這就有幾個可能性 一個就是找新的材料
Then this is a new one just mentioned, this is actually just now
那這個是一個新的剛才講的 這個其實剛才就是
This is the first quick delivery made by Academician Wu Maokun.
這是吳茂坤院士當初做出來 第一個做出來的快產
People develop it into a plane
人家把它展成一個平面
This is an incredible technique on one material
這是用很不得了的技術 在一個材料上
I don’t know how to say this in Chinese Stranding Titanium Oxide
這個我不曉得中文怎麼講 Stranding Titanium Oxide
On top of this material, grow a layer on a very thin material
在這個材料上面 很薄的材料上長一層
It is one layer of iron and T, iron and C, one layer of iron C
就是一層的鐵跟T 鐵跟C 鐵C一層
Then they measure the superconducting temperature, there are many papers
然後他們去量超導溫度 這有好多paper
It came out in this journal that the superconducting temperature should reach 100
在這個期刊裡面出來 說這個超導溫度要到100
09 degrees
09度
it must be shaken to death
它一定要被震死
But 65 degrees is probably no problem.
但是65度是已經大概沒問題了
109 degrees will shock you to death
109度還要震死
But that temperature is only 8 degrees higher than the original temperature of this thing
但那溫度比原來它這個東西的溫度只有8度
It's time to make a wish without fainting
無冒昏願是做出來的時候
That temperature is only 8 degrees
那溫度只有8度
Now people use this method
現在人家用這種方法
When it is not the same as it is made
跟它不太一樣做出來的時候
why?
那個為什麼呢
that may be new physics on this surface
那可能是在這個表面有新的物理
This is the mechanism we just disturbed
這是我們剛剛的擾心的機制
This is what experiments tell us
這就是實驗告訴我們
The temperature here is much, much higher than before.
這個的溫度比原來高很多很多
This mechanism may not be the original
這個機制可能不是原來的機制
Then it has a new possibility
那它又有種新的可能性
that's certainly possible
那當然有可能
Because it is possible that the biomass here has a great influence on it
因為有可能這裡的生質對它影響很大
But here the biomass influence is very large causing this electron
但這裡的生質影響很大造成這個電子
because it is compartment
因為是隔層
The electron is still here
這個電子還在這裡
So I didn't trap it very hard
所以沒有把它trap的很厲害
Didn't dig it deep just now
沒有把它剛才那個緊挖得很深
so it can run fast
所以它可以跑得很快
But electrons are strong
但是電子作用很強
So it is possible that its superconducting temperature increases
所以有可能它的超導溫度增加
This lead is a hot end of term doing research
這個導拉是正在做研究的一個很熱的期末
You can see that this paper is very popular at the end of the term
你可以看到這個paper都是非常熱門的期末
This guide pull is an interesting idea
這個導拉是一個有趣的想法
Some people have thought about using this interface to control
就是以前有人也想過用這個界面來控制
an electron in a layer
一個電子在一個一層
that rope is on another layer
那個繩子在另外一層
or positively charged on another layer
或者正電在另外一層
Your negative charge is on another layer
你這個負電在另外一層
How to control? This Nimi technology is here
怎麼控制?這個耐米技術來了
We can now control the material
我們現在可以來控制材料
Think of ways to make a variety of such interfaces to
想想辦法做出各種不同的這種界面來
This can also increase the operating temperature
這個也可以增加操作溫度
Another more exciting thing is that under high pressure
另外一個更精彩的是在加高壓之下
Just now we said that increasing the high pressure is a
剛才我們講加高壓是一支用
But this high pressure is as high as 200GP
但這個高壓是高到200GP
There are only a few in the world
全世界只有幾台
Someone use this ability to do this high pressure
有人用這個能力做這個高壓
The person who mainly made this
這個主要的做的這個人
I used to do a post with that Wang Heguangyuan
以前是跟那個王河光院做post打
Aremes
Aremes
they recently discovered
他們最近發現
Everyone thinks of Liu Huaqing smelling bad
劉華清大家都想到很難聞的
In Jiang Mishan, you may often smell some
在蔣秘山大概常常會聞到一些
This is of course poisonous proof
這個當然是有毒的破證
not good
不好的
very bad gas
非常糟糕的氣體
this is fine now
這個現在沒事幹
Squeeze the shit out of it
把這些糟糕的氣體把它壓
Physicists are crazy
物理學家很發瘋的
Of course it makes sense
當然還有道理了
squeeze it down
把它壓壓壓壓
He said 200 shower 3 degrees
他說200淋3度
Oops
糟糕
Of course if he's proven right
當然如果證明他對的
This is the job Noble talked about again.
這個又是諾白講的工作
But this problem is difficult to prove
但是這個問題是很難證明
Because few people have 200
因為沒有幾個人有200
Gagapet kettle
Gagapetskjel
This instrument and especially complex
這個儀器和尤其是複雜
he does
他做
This is of course an early theory
這個當然事實上是很早理論
let me talk about theory
就我講理論
Anyway, it doesn't cost anything
反正不花什麼錢就算過
Said that maybe in such a material
說也許在這樣子的材料裡面
Kiyomi
這個清見
Because everyone thinks clearly
因為清大家都想得很清
So vibrate so much
所以振動得很厲害
high frequency of vibration
振動的頻率很高
Farmers’ comments are also very high, which is related to the BCS theory just mentioned
農民評論也很高,就跟剛才講BCS理論有關
It is easy to operate and the temperature will increase
就是容易操作溫度會增加
That is what I want to say, if farmers are not orthodox, they must not operate
就是我要講,農民不正統就一定沒操作
The more orthodox, the better
正統的越厲害越好
The higher the comment, the better
那種評論越高越好
So very early on Prediction said
所以很早就有Prediction說
Theoretically speaking, it’s more than three hundred. Of course, no one believes it when they come here often
理論的就說,都是三百多,當然常來沒人相信
How could it be more than 200 or 300 to do this job?
怎麼可能兩百多、三百多做這個勤
But these they do, of course I don't know if this is this
但是這些他們做的,當然這個是不是這個我不曉得
Of course this is, because everyone knows that it is easy for electrons to escape
當然這個就是,因為這個親大家曉得很容易電子跑掉
But it is also easy to become H-minor, there are two electrons coming
但是親也很容易變成H-minor,有兩個電子過來
one more electron
多了一個電子
So it's kind of like Cooper Pet
所以就有點像Cooper Pet
From here to here there is a couple
從這裡到這裡就是有一對
so this is interesting
所以這個就有趣了
Is there an extra physics
是不是這裡面有額外的這個物理
Not so simple physics
也不是這麼簡單的物理
Of course this has not been confirmed
當然這個還沒被證實
I'm just talking, that is to say, I have some new ideas
我只是講的話,就是說又有些新的idea
That is, if we find a stronger force
就是如果我們有找更強的作用力
It is not necessary to say that we cannot
不見得說,我們不能夠
But of course how do you prevent what I just said
但是當然你怎麼防止我剛才講的
nothing else to add
沒有別的太來增的
because you tied it too tight
因為你把它綁得太緊
It's simple and it's not too tight
那簡單它又沒有綁太緊
Because the person itself will vibrate very much
因為親本身又會很對振動
so maybe not tied too tight
所以可能沒有綁太緊
It's hard to tie a kiss too tight
很難把親綁得太緊的
because it is very light
因為它很輕
So the problem is under this
所以這個問題就是在這下面
There may also be other operators
也有可能會有別的操作體
Of course you will often see it in newspapers
當然你會常常在報場常常看到
And who found another operator
又誰又發現一個操作體
this will be a lot
這個會很多了
we used to joke a lot
我們以前就有常常開玩笑
this is called
這個叫做
We are called UFO and everyone knows that
我們叫UFO大家都曉得就是
Unidentified Flying Object
Unidentified Flying Object
It's just an unidentified flying object.
就是沒有被證實的飛行物體
what is flying
就是飛跌了什麼
We often say that this superconducting world also has
我們常常講這個超導界也有
USO Unidentified Superconducting Object
USO Unidentified Superconducting Object
superconducting
超導
many people posted
很多人發佈
i see 300 degrees
我看到300度
I saw 200 for a while
我看到200度過一陣子
head pass
頭通完待
haven't found it for so many years
還沒找到那麼多年來
But of course there is some evidence here
但是這裡當然是有一些證據
Some of its rugs still look obvious
它的有些地毯看起來還明顯
But it's obviously early. Why on earth?
但是這個顯然還早 到底為什麼
I don't know if it's really too high
是不是真的超到 還不曉得
But this question
可是這個真詢
Lume Temporary called this dream
Lume Temporary叫做這個夢
i think we'll always have
我想我們永遠都會有
I thank you all for this
這個我就謝謝大家
I also thank my assistants
我也謝謝我幾位助理
Professor Chen Yingqian gave me a lot of slides
跟陳影乾教授給我很多投影片
Principal Wu Maokun gave me some slides
吳茂坤校長給我一些投影片
but thanks for their help
但是謝謝他們的幫忙
thank you all
謝謝大家
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
well timed
時間控制得很好
good
好
you
你
Do you have any questions?
大家有沒有問題
or
或者
please
請
Thank you teacher for a very wonderful speech
謝謝老師非常精采的演講
Let me first admit that I am a student of biology
我先承認我自己是學生物的
so
所以
I don't really understand the details
詳細的我並不是非常的理解
but in my mind
但是我印象中
I used to send
以前就是發
It has been said since the beginning of the year
從年一開始也有講
start as a single atomic material
一開始是單一的原子的材料
Later, it gradually became multi-atomic
後來慢慢變成多個原子的
In my impression, at that super high temperature
我印象中在那個超溫高
When the super-heated high temperature jumps
超溫的高溫跳躍的那個時候
It seems to have been predicted
好像曾經用預測說
the composite material
那個複合材料的話
Is the atom in it replaced by which one?
裡面的原子是不是用哪一個去代換
it may become high temperature
它就有可能變成高溫
Then it was math
後來是用數學算
Forget it, which element may be extrapolated later
算了以後外推可能是哪個元素
The substitution was successful.
代換進去結果成功了
That's especially new from what you introduced today
那從您今天介紹的特別是新的
Two cases in 2015
2015年二例
that's what i think
那個是我想
i think at that time
我想那個時候
Of course they're a bit disrespectful
當然他們有些無貌分
This is quite a lot
這個不少
The blue quilt is the same one that won the Nobel Prize
藍被同樣那個拿諾貝爾講
he is not for this reason
他不是為了這個原因
His reason is not calculation
他的原因不是計算
His idea was to increase the effect of electroplasma
他的想法是增加電生質的作用
he knows this
他曉得這個
usually this
通常這個
These are ceramic materials weird
這些是陶瓷材料很奇怪
I just talked about these new high temperatures
我剛才講這些新的高溫
The Blue Bell of Taobao body is the same
淘寶體這個藍貝爾同樣
Mao Kun Zhu Jin Weapon
茂昆朱金武器
they found out
他們發現是
ceramic material is very fragile
是陶瓷材料很脆弱的
That's what you can't imagine saying
那個是你不可以想像說
it becomes superconducting
它會變超導
but he made it superconducting
但他把它變成超導
So they know that there are electric
所以他們曉得有電生
So the original Bandau's Mule was for electric birth to many people
所以當初那個Bandau's Mule是為了電生子很多人
He did it to see if the temperature was up to
他去做的看看有沒有溫度到
As a result, he found that the temperature was very high
結果他發覺溫度很高
Of course, now we know that he has nothing to do with the effect of electrogenesis
當然現在我們知道他根本跟電生子作用的沒有關係
It's not for that reason that it becomes over
不是因為那個原因變成超到
but usually the right answer for the wrong reasons
但是通常都是為了錯誤的原因找到正確的答案
That's okay too
那這個也沒關係了
This is what science is all about.
這個就是做科學都是這樣子
Then he is single, you just talked about calculating
那他的單身你剛才講說計算
In fact, many people have calculated many materials and said that the temperature is very high
其實有很多人計算很多材料說溫度很高
Experiments that were wrong at first proved to be wrong
當初錯誤的實驗證明都錯誤
we are not right yet
我們現在還沒對
So I just said the last one, I don’t know if it’s right
所以我剛才講最後那個不曉得對不對
Most of them are 99% wrong
大部分99%都不對
what you imagine is not real
你想像的不是真的
Yeah, I want to ask this too
是啊我也是想請教這個
Because that microscope that just looked at that tunnel
因為剛剛看那個隧道的那個顯微鏡
It looks like another rule
它看起來其實是另外一個規律
You also mentioned that it may have another physical law
你也有提到它有可能有另外的物理上的規律
In fact, it is not clear
其實還不清楚
have what
有什麼
another physical phenomenon
另外的物理上的那個現象
That is, can these be described by mathematics?
那是這些是不是可以用數學描述
I think the extrapolated way
我覺得外推的方式
is described by mathematics
就是用數學描述
you don't really quantify
你沒有真正的量化
Then you can't really predict
然後你不能真正的預測
Many experiments are useless
很多實驗是沒有用的
theory is to quantify
理論就是要量化
It is useful to predict
要預測才有用
So all the talking things have to be spread out
所以所有的講的東西都要散得出來
only useful
才有用
so must
所以一定要
so even though
所以雖然這麼
I talked about such a miraculous quantum state
我講了這麼神奇的量子態
macroscopic quantum state
巨觀量子態
Giants are rare
巨觀量才是很少的
Then this is beyond
那這個超到
If in the test
如果在試聞當中
I say this
我說這個
so it's a big deal
所以是不得了的事情
because only
因為只有
Only after sniffing our little quantum mechanics
只有在試聞我們小的量子力學
should not be very important
應該不是很重要的
Then if there is a huge amount
那居然如果可以有巨觀量
Of course it's a great thing
當然是很偉大的事情
this is difficult
這個是很難的事情
Because the quantum state must
因為量子態一定要
should be kept at a very low temperature
應該是放在很低的溫度
small size
很小的尺寸裡
but now it's about
但現在講的是
It was a big size just now
剛才都是很大的尺寸
you have seen
你們已經看到了
The performance of the quantum state
量子態的表現了
This is likely to have more
這個是有可能會有更
So we wish to find the temperature
所以我們希望找到溫度
All four temperatures are superconducting
四溫都是超導
You have to reheat it so it doesn't superconduct
你要把它再加溫它才不超導
this is dream
這個是 dream
It would be a very good thing if it came out
如果出來的話當然是非常好的事情
This is still difficult
這個現在還困難
There are a lot more
還有很多
Of course it is because of difficulties
當然就是因為有困難才有
we have research to do
我們才有研究要做
please
請
ask the professor
請教教授
The one that just experimented with the one that floated
剛實驗的那個浮起來的那個
It's also called the principle of Chifu
也是叫那個馳腐的原理
Yes or no
是不是
right
對
Excuse me, the rotten train in Japan that you just introduced
請問像你剛介紹的日本的那個馳腐列車
this is the principle
就是這個原理
So that means their train is running
那這麼說他們那個列車在跑
Will there be a lot of smoke?
是不是一樣都會有很多煙
No
沒有
certainly
當然
we can't help it
我們沒辦法了
if we cover you up
如果我們上面把你蓋起來
Then put another train on top of it
然後在上面再擺一個火車在上面
Toys can be compared and analyzed like this
玩具才能做得比較分析就這樣子
Put another toy on top
上面再擺一個玩具
You can't see the train from above
火車在上面就看不見
just sealed it up inside
就把它封起來了在裡面
that liquid doesn't evaporate
那個液態不會蒸發
it has a cooling system all closed
它有一個冷卻系統全部是封閉的
This way it will last longer
這樣子就會保障久一點
This cooling system
這冷卻系
So probably save this
所以大概省這個
it keeps it sealed
它讓它封起來
you can't see the smoke
你看不到煙
So their shameful car is going
所以他們那個恥腐烈車在走
smoke is invisible
煙是看不到的
we taiwan
我們台灣
I remember almost 20 years ago
我記得差不多20多年前
That explosive magazine has talked about this shameful car
那個爆裝雜誌都有談論到這個恥腐烈車
But to this day, there is still no Taiwan
可是到今天會不會台灣還是沒有
then ask the professor
那請問教授
Will there be superconducting cars in the future?
在未來會不會有超導烈車
Thanks
謝謝
Japan is ready to build one
日本已經預備蓋一個
from tokyo to i think it was osaka
從東京到我想記得是大阪
This is already a national strategy
這個是已經國家型策略已經定了
It's going to build this in 2025
它要2025年的時候蓋這個
superconducting car
超導烈車嗎
right
對
Of course it is not completely superconducting now
當然它現在不是完全用超導
i listen now
我現在聽
Sounds like it's not exactly hot tide
聽起來聽說它不是完全有高溫潮的
I said it also uses some low temperature tide
我講它也用一些低溫潮的
it has some hybrid designs
它有一些混合設計
Because all use high temperature tide
因為全部用高溫潮的
can be expensive now
現在可能很貴
too expensive
太貴了
so it may now have a
所以它現在可能有一個
But this cryogenic industry
但是這個低溫產業
It is Japan's century-old plan
是日本的百年大計畫
Japan now has
日本現在有個
Japan seems to like to make a hundred-year plan
日本好像是喜歡做一百年的計畫
planning
規劃
Then it has a big plan
那它這個有個大規劃
cryogenic industry
就是要把低溫產業
become the most important industry in their country
變成他們國家最重要的產業
What is cryogenic industry
什麼叫低溫產業
That is, making many things is related to low temperature
就是造很多東西都跟低溫有關
There are many benefits of low temperature
低溫的話就有很多好處
So what are they going to do with these low temperature
所以他們要怎麼做這些低溫
So build this superconducting train
所以造這個超導的列車
is the plan of one of its elephants
是它其中一個大象的計畫
so you just mentioned
所以您剛有提到
The high temperature tide guide and the low tide guide
那個高溫潮導跟低音潮導
The cost of low temperature tidal conduction is much lower
那低溫潮導的成本是低很多的
because it's been years
因為它已經很多年了
Done
做了
Therefore, the trouble caused by high temperature tide is just mentioned
所以高溫潮導的麻煩就是剛才講
That is, it is more fragile than it is a ceramic material
就是它比它是陶瓷材料比較脆弱
OK, the other Mr. Lu, these are good materials
OK,那其他那個呂老這些都是很好的材料
It's easier to do, the same
就比較容易做的,同了
I mean those blue pill cakes
就是說那些藍藥餅
The ingredients of the blue medicine cake just mentioned are relatively easy to make
剛才講的藍藥餅這些材料是比較容易做的
less easy to consume
比較不容易消耗
Yes, it is not easy, because it is relatively flexible and flexible to make this kind of
對,不是比較容易,因為比較有韌性彈性做成這種
You know the cable, you say you can bend it
你知道電纜,你說你能不能彎啊
It's broken after a bend, it's okay
一彎就斷了還得了,不得了
That electric current is incredible, so it absolutely cannot happen
那個電流是不得了的,所以絕對不能發生的
When doing this kind of thing is the most difficult to apply
做這種東西最難做到應用的時候
safety is the most important
安全性是最重要
But security is
可是安全性就是
Many problems with shooting are not physical problems
對拍攝很多問題不是物理的問題
It's about mechanics and engineering.
就是機械跟工程的問題
that's hard
那就很難
So why did he only do one kilometer for so many years?
所以他為什麼做那麼多年只做到一公里
The long is what you want to do so long
長的就是你要做到那麼長
pull such a long line
拉那麼長的線
Everyone you can bend, right?
每一個人你可以彎了對不對
The cable can't be bent
電纜怎麼都不能彎了
It must be able to bend, right?
一定可以彎了對不對
then you will be fine
那你要不出問題
that is difficult
那個是難的
Of course they've been improving and you can see that.
當然他們一直在進步可以看出來了
These countries are doing their best
這幾個國家是拼老命在做
always improving
一直在進步
Because this is a big industry
因為這個是大產業
Who can do it? It's a very good job, of course.
做出來誰有辦法產這個做得非常好當然
whoever has a very big industry
誰就非常大的產業
this is no problem
這個是沒問題的事
so this is what they do
所以這個是他們在做的
Taiwan does not have this aspect
那台灣比較沒有這方面
thank you professor thank you
謝謝教授 謝謝
I would like to ask you, Professor, what you just said
我想請問一下就是教授你剛剛有講到就是
CurvePair is electronics and childbirth
CurvePair就是電子跟生子
Its interaction causes overrun to
它的interaction造成超到
but my problem is
可是我的問題是
When you use a single or a single cooling down to 1K 2K
當你用一台單或一台還降溫到1K 2K
At this time, giving birth should be
這個時候生子應該是
Your Ginger should not vibrate
你的金格應該是不會震盪
That is, childbirth should be fixed there.
就是生子應該是固定在那裡
I just can't
就是我無法
Just understanding is how the electronics interact with the child at this time
就是理解就是電子這個時候怎麼跟生子做interaction
This is what I just said
這就是我剛剛講就是在
absolute temperature zero
絕對溫度零度的話
The atoms and ions will still oscillate
這個原子和離子還是會震盪
this is quantum mechanics
這就是量子力學
Otherwise, the uncertainty principle is violated
要不然就違反不確定原理
We all know the uncertainty principle
大家知道不確定原理
is that you must never have a thing
就是你絕對不能有一個東西
my position
我的position
The position of space is immobile
空間的位置是不動
because if you don't move at all
因為如果完全不動
The kinetic energy of that thing is infinite
那個東西的動能就是infinite
unlimited
無限
is impossible
是不可能發生的
so it must move
所以它一定會動
will definitely move
一定會整動
So why is superconductivity so difficult to say?
所以這個為什麼超導那麼難講
That is, it is all related to quantum mechanics
就是它都跟量子力學是
It's all about quantum mechanics
全部都是跟量子力學有關的
Classical mechanics is completely inexplicable
古典力學是完全不能解釋
Of course it was 1911 and no one wanted to appreciate
當然也是1911年沒有人要appreciate
After I understand quantum mechanics, I want to say
等到量子力學都懂了以後就想說
This is a full quantum
這個是全量子的一個
Then you just said it will still move
那你剛才講它還是會整動
you can't keep it from moving
你沒辦法不讓它整動
this is impossible
這個是不可能發生的
So this shock is bound to happen
所以這個震盪是一定會發生的
That's how it is
那也就有這樣子的
this is
這個就是
he sounds bad
他的聽起來是壞處
Actually it's his benefit
其實是他的好處
There are so many strange phenomena
才有這麼多奇怪的現象
If it could happen in the quantum world
如果可以發生在量子世界
These strange phenomena will all appear
這些奇怪的現象就會通通出現
He has a new statement
他就有新的表態出來了
Not the usual world we are familiar with
不是平常我們熟悉的世界
No
沒有
Can
可以
The teacher just mentioned superconductivity
老師剛剛有提到超導的話
we take the battery away
我們把電池拿走
The current will still run inside
電流還會在裡面跑
May I ask if this situation is impossible?
請問這個狀況跟不可能發生的那種
have what
有什麼
That is to say, I made a machine
就是說我做了一個機器
I don't need to attack its energy
我不用攻擊它能量
it can work forever
它可以永遠永遠的工作
But the current you just said keeps running
但是您剛剛說的電流一直跑
it sounds like this
聽起來好像是這種樣子
that's because
那個是因為
this is here
這個是在這裡
because this is here
因為這個是在這裡
It can manipulate state, it can use
它可以操導狀態,它可以用
You can't talk about motivation
你不能講擁動機
If you use the motivation to say that you still want to use this
你如果把擁動機是說你還想去用這個
if you put this, this, this
如果你把這個,這個,這個
The flywheel just mentioned is
剛才講那個飛輪就是
It's done now
現在已經做出來了
Just steer it around
就操導它一直轉
The purpose of its rotation is to transfer kinetic energy
它轉的目的就是把動能
Because rotation is kinetic energy
因為轉就是動能
put energy in
把能量都存進去
that can store a lot of energy
那都可以存很大能量
Because it depends on the volume and shape of your work
因為看你的做的體積等等的形狀
can be very big
可以很大很大的
Then you put it in, how do you take it out?
那你存進去,那你要怎麼拿出來呢
Then you have to connect to another thing
那你要接到另外一個東西上
it will turn slower and slower
它就會越轉越慢了
Because energy is conserved
因為把能量是守衡的
no motivation
沒有什麼擁動機
There is something wrong with this word
這個話就是有點問題
This is not a motive here
這個這裡不是擁動機
Its energy is also conserved
它這個能量也有守衡的
Then if you take it off, it's gone
那你如果把它拿掉,它就沒有了
OK, this is
OK,這個是
Energy is always in balance
能量永遠是守衡的
OK, energy will never come out when you are empty
OK,絕對不會空就能量出來的
There are several laws in this physics
這個物理的裡面有幾個定律是
without exception
沒有例外過的
I would like to ask, does the current definition of superconductivity mean that its resistance must be zero?
我想請問一下,那個超導現在定義就是說它的電阻一定是0嗎?
Or when you said the number of degrees in the data just now?
還是說那你當初剛才那個數據上說在多少度的時候
Its resistivity also has a value, what does that mean?
它的電阻率還有一個值那是什麼意思?
No, it has value in Siwenhao, but it has no value below a certain TCE, it is 0
不是,就在四文豪它有值,但到某一個TCE以下就沒有值,就0啊
The so-called superconducting train used in Japan also uses this phenomenon of reaching zero to let...
那日本用的那個所謂的超導列車它也是用這種到0的這種現象去讓...
That's right, what you saw just now is the high-temperature superconductor here, and the spirited one floated up just now
對呀,剛才你們看到的就是這裡高溫超導,剛才那個拼靈的浮起來
It is superconducting there. A few pieces of superconducting material here had a resistance of 0 at that time.
它就是在那超導它,這裡幾塊超導的材料那時候就是電阻得0啊
That must be 0, that is, as I just said, it must be 0
那是一定得0啊,就是我剛講它非得0不可
Then if it is not 0, that thing will be taken soon, it will not run for so long
那如果不得0,那個東西很快就帶,它不會跑那麼久啊
It's just because of its metal, right, you... you need to get the battery
就是憑它金屬你對不對,你這個...你拿電池去弄一下
It will have this man named Eddie Curran, which is what I just said
它會有這個叫Eddie Curran,就是剛才講的會
It's gone in no time
那可是一下子就沒了
If you want to keep adding a lot
你如果要一直弄加很多
A lot of your hands will be hot
很多你這個手就會燙了
Because the metal will be hot
因為金屬會燙起來了
They all turn into resistors and dissipate energy.
都變成電阻都把能量消耗掉了
but not here
可是這裡不會
it just keeps running
它就一直跑
The only thing that didn't end up was because it evaporated
那唯一最後沒有的是因為蒸發了
take this liquid
把這個液態
but evaporated
但蒸發掉了
it's not too early
它不超早了
it warmed up
它溫度回升了
That's why the price stopped
所以才停價了
but the question just asked
但是剛才問的問題
if i seal it up
如果我把它封起來
It's fine if it's sealed well
封得好好就沒問題
Now there are many laboratories
現在有很多實驗室
These liquids are all sealed.
裝的這些液態都是封起來了
so it's been inside
所以它一直在裡面
it doesn't evaporate
它不會蒸發
that can be a long time
那就可以很久很久了
then there is no such problem
那就沒這個問題
So why save energy
所以說為什麼節能
Why do they think this is energy saving
為什麼他們覺得這個是節能
It saves electricity compared to usual current trains
比平常現在的火車都省電
there is a reason
就是個原因
You just need to close it up
你只要做好封閉好了
It's not that hard when the machine arrives
這個機械到了這不是很難的事情
you don't have to do it again
你就不要再去重新弄
don't add oil
也不要加石油了
Oil sells nothing
油了什麼都不銷
then ask again
那再問一下
When the current of this material runs with zero resistance
這種材料在電阻為零的情況下的電流跑的時候
Is there any damage or consumption of this material?
這個材料有沒有什麼損傷或是消耗
No
沒有
as far as i know no
據我知道是沒有
because it doesn't hit anything
因為它不撞到什麼東西
No, you and I don't have resistors
不是 我跟妳講沒有電阻
so it didn't hit the good stuff
所以它沒有撞到好東西
no way to consume it
沒有辦法去消耗它
ok, is there any more
好 還有沒有
But theoretically no
不過理論上是沒有
Of course I don't know what your question is
當然我不曉得你問的問題是
After your engineer
你engineer以後
it must still have some condition
它一定還是有一些狀況
it's better
它比較好
the only thing is
唯一就是
Yes, the only thing is in transform energy conversion
對 唯一就是在transform能量轉換
Switch from this to another time
從這個轉換到別的時候
There may be some energy savings there will be
可能有一些能量省耗一定會
Because you're not everything manipulative
因為你不是每一個東西都是操導嗎
No
沒有
Because usually when the energy conversion
因為通常在能量轉換的時候
You need to convert this energy
你要把這個能量轉換
Energy summoned into another energy
能量召喚成另外一种能量
into electric energy or into mk
变成电能或者是变成mk
Of course you will have some provincial numbers
你当然会有些省号了
Energy summoning is like burning gasoline to become a machine leader
能量召喚就像烧汽油变成机器的弄领
You won't be 100% efficient
你不会百分之百的效率了
The problem with this energy call
这能量召喚的问题
But it itself has no province number energy
但它本身是没有省号能量
But when you use it or facilitate it
但是你在使用它或者促成它的时候
Of course there will be some energy provinces
当然会有些能量省号
it's inevitable
这是免不了的
I want to ask the teacher
我想请问老师
Is Ci Fu superconducting?
那慈福都是超导吗
Or is it like the one from Shanghai Cifu?
还是说像上海慈福的这种
Is it still a type of superconductor?
它还是超导的一种吗
Yes, but it doesn't have to be superconducting
对 但是不一定要超导
that's what i just said
就是我刚才讲的
first time i show that
第一次我秀那个
That is, you usually take a metal
就是你平常拿一个金属
Take a magnetist's back and go back
拿一个磁铁匠的回来回去
In fact, there will be inverse
它其实里面就会有产生反过来
you will
你就会
if you are strong enough
如果你够强的话
you'll feel it resist
你就会感觉到它有反抗力
just be kind
就可以慈福就好
so which two
所以哪两个
It is equal to South Pole to South Pole
就是等于南极对南极
North Pole to North Pole can float
北极对北极就可以浮起来了
But this thing is not very stable, just like what I said just now, it is not very stable,
但這個東西不太穩,就像剛才講的,不太穩,
Because you have to face it just right, and if you tilt it a little bit, you will be in trouble, and the trouble will be reversed.
因為你要對著正好,你稍歪一點就麻煩了,麻煩就倒了,
It's not very stable, but you can't do it without instability, stability is the most important thing.
這不是很穩的做的,但是要做著火車道道不能不穩,穩定是最重要的。
So I just said that another group repaired your superconducting hair, and it has the magnetic flux of the magnetic field line locked inside.
所以剛才講另外一伙修你超導發,它有那個磁力線磁通量在裡面鎖住了,
So it is equivalent to having a thread inside, clamping it, so it is very stable,
所以它等於有跟線在裡面,把它夾住了,所以它很穩,
Like the magnet just now, you can see that it is very stable, very stable, and if you look carefully, it is very stable, very stable,
像剛才那個磁,你看那個這樣子倒很穩了,非常穩,你仔細看是很穩很穩的,
You can drill like this by yourself, right? It drills, you can see that it follows the magnetic force line,
自己就可以這樣子鑽了,對不對,它鑽你看它是順著這個磁力線,
It flew out without drilling that day, of course not so fast, but it can be seen that it drilled along this way,
當天沒鑽就飛出去了,當然沒那麼快了,但是可以看出來它是順著這個鑽了,
That's very strange, isn't it? People don't have a track, and it's nothing. Why does it drill along this?
那就很奇怪對不對,人家沒有軌道,又沒什麼,它為什麼順著這個鑽?
Then if there is a superconducting train in the future, it will be safer than a running train.
那如果說將來有超導列車,那就是會比馳服列車更安全了。
Superconductivity is also a kind of surrender
超導也是辭服的一種
But wouldn't superconductivity be safer?
但是超導是不是會更安全
More power saving, is it safer?
更省電,是不是更安全不?
But if it's more than 500 kilometers, I hope it's safe
但如果超五百多公里的話,希望很安全
they are going to try now
他們現在要試著做
so why would they do it
所以他們才要為什麼做
I just saw that Japan was trying to make a one-kilometer-long
剛才看到日本是他們試做一公里長
have been trying for a long time
已經試了很久了
This kilometer-long superconducting train
這個一公里長的超導列車
right ? that of course is to try
對不對?那當然就是要試
Many are engineering problems
很多是工程問題
Actually speaking, many of those things are projects.
其實講出來就是很多那個東西是工程
Of course, one is the issue of price, the other is the issue of engineering
當然一個價錢的問題,一個是工程的問題
Now mainly these two issues
現在主要是這兩個問題
I think it's probably technically resolved.
我想技術上大概都解決
Because they also make cables, America makes so many cables
因為他們也做電纜,美國做了那麼多電纜
Also trying to test this problem
也是在試測試這個問題
That is to say, everything else is a supporting engineering problem now.
就是說現在其他都是配套的工程問題
is more important
是比較重要的
Then the cost of this suit and the cost of superconductivity
那這個辭服的成本跟超導的成本
superconductor is more expensive
是超導比較貴一點
Superconductors are now more expensive
現在超導比較貴
Yes, this high-temperature superconductor is of course more expensive to manufacture now
對,這個高溫超導現在做當然比較貴
Of course it's also because he doesn't have mass production.
當然也是因為他沒什麼量產
Wait until they progress to mass production
等到他們再進步到真的有量產的時候
Of course it's different
當然又不一樣了
this is totally different
這個又完全不一樣
Of course countries are competing
當然各國都在競爭
So the cost is the same for large quantities
所以量大成本就一樣
right
對
The advantage is that the film energy saves a lot
那他的好處是電影能源省了很多
that's not noisy
那又不吵
he floated
他浮起來了
that's fast, right?
那又快對不對
not noisy
又不吵
no sound
沒有聲音
Of course it's good, right?
當然是很好的對不對
If it is floating in front
如果是浮在前面
I think it must be very comfortable to sit on
我想坐在上面一定很舒服
I was wondering right?
我就在想對不對
I sat in the one in Beishang
我坐過那個北上海那個
That's not bad
那不錯
Of course he wasn't fast enough.
當然他那個不夠快就是了
all at once
就一下子
but that's fine
不過那個就很好
that floats is a good thing
那浮起來是很好的事
You said that it will be faster if you overtake it in the future
你說以後超倒了還會更快
will be faster
還會更快
certainly
當然
Of course
當然了
Will
一定會
Technology is improving every day
技術是每天都在進步的
good last step
好最後一步
Teacher, you just said that
老師你剛剛說那個
Energy conversion consumes energy
能量轉換的話會耗能
But just now you have experienced so much
可是剛剛到現在你體驗那麼多
The electrons are swapped again, this and that
電子又交換,又換這個又換那個
Then you said they were dancing together as a metaphor
然後你又說他們在一起跳舞來比喻
dancing is tiring
跳舞也會累
Then why do they change their own words?
那為什麼他們自己換兩換句
Doesn't seem to consume energy
好像都不會消耗能量
No, this is the look of this super old lady
不是吧,電子這個就是這個超老太的神情
It's not an exchange to exchange energy
它不是去交換能量的交換
Because your electron is here, right?
因為你電子本來就在這裡嘛,對不對
Then when I actually exchange like this
那我事實上這樣子交換的時候
when you swap with your neighbor
你跟隔壁交換的時候
You don't imagine it's tiring for you
你不會想像對你來講很累
You have to change the chair with him, right?
你要跟他換一個椅子對不對
But I just said that for electronics
但是我剛才講對電子來講
He will be tired if he doesn't change
他不換他才比較累
Because of this Helenberg Uncertainty Principle
因為這個Helenberg不確定原理
On the contrary, it is very comfortable
換反而很舒殘
The more you change, the better
越換越多越好
So electrons in quantum teraroots
所以電子在量子太根
Our usual thinking is wrong
我們的平常的想法是不對的
because in quantum too
因為是在量子太
he is not sure
他不確定
That's how the uncertainty principle in mechanics sounds
那样子力学不确定原理听起来
usually very simple
平常都讲得很简单
In fact, the impact of the uncertainty principle is very far-reaching.
其实不确定原理的影响是非常深远的
this is
这个是
Of course we don't know why nature
当然我们不曉得为什么自然界
uncertainty principle
会有不确定原理
But it obviously has this principle
但它显然有这个原理
And that's what you just said
而且就是你刚刚讲的问题
it gets better and better
它越换越换越好
It doesn't like it and stays there
它不喜欢反而待在那里不动
is high energy
是能量很高的
so it won't happen
所以不会发生
in the real material
在真正的这个材料里面
this won't happen
不会发生这个事情
unless you have great strength
除非你有很大的力量
hold it hard
硬要把它拉住
that's what i just said
就是我刚刚讲的
then it won't exceed
那就不会超到了
Then this can't be helped
那这个就没办法了
Otherwise, it's best to change
要不然到最好换
good i think
好 我想
director
理所长也
I just said that everyone is
我刚刚说大家都是
this is very well prepared
这个准备非常充分
Then I worked hard
然后也毛足了力
this
这个
take a very difficult question
把一個非常艱深的問題
and let everyone know at least a little bit about
然後讓大家至少有一點瞭解
I am also very grateful to these two students
那也非常感謝這兩位同學
this i just saw that
這個我剛剛看到那個
The barrel of the liquid bomb is there
液態彈的桶在那裡
That's a heavy thing to move here
那個是很重的東西都搬過來
move all the props
什麼道具都搬過來
I just hope you can get some
就是希望大家能夠得到一些
At least some knowledge
至少有一些knowledge
This achieves the purpose of our knowledge miss
這就達到我們的知識想念的目的
Well, we are very grateful to Li Xiugang
好 我們非常謝謝李秀崗